The United Kingdom has an epic history
and a wealth of secrets still to
uncover.
Every year hundreds of archaeologists
dig,
dive,
and sieve to find clues
to add to the great historical jigsaw of
our ancestors' lives.
>> You know when people say what's the best
thing you've ever found, guys? This.
>> I'm Professor Alice Roberts.
This year we've uncovered some
astonishing finds and made some truly
groundbreaking [music] discoveries.
>> Wow, look at that.
>> Each team of archaeologists has been
armed with a dig diary camera so they
can record their discoveries as they
happen.
>> That is brilliant. Dave, I love you.
>> Our roving archaeologist, Dr. Nisha
McSweeney, is out on the digs.
>> Who are we looking at?
>> It's royal.
>> And I'll be inviting the teams to bring
in their finds for closer analysis. That
is absolutely beautiful.
In this special edition of Digging for
Britain, we're exploring the archaeology
of World War II.
We're joining digs from across the
country to give us an insight into the
lives of those who lived and fought
during the war from the physical
evidence they left behind.
We'll witness the raising of a World War
II bomber from the depths of the English
Channel,
the unearthing of one of Hitler's feared
V2 rockets,
and an excavation of a hostel where
young Holocaust survivors were brought
after the war.
>> Welcome to Digging for Britain.
>> I've come to the Imperial War Museum in
Duxford, Cambridgeshire.
It was from this airfield that the first
Spitfires took off for the Battle of
Britain in July 1940.
Countless Allied missions flew from
airfields right across Britain heading
for Nazi-occupied Europe. But some
planes never made it that far.
And we head now to the Solent where a
chance discovery has prompted a
large-scale diving operation.
They are attempting to recover the
amazingly intact remains of a Second
World War bomber.
The excavation is located 500 m
offshore, not far from Gosport Harbor.
It was here in 2018 that the National
Grid planned to lay an electricity cable
to France.
And they first needed to conduct an
underwater survey of the seafloor.
>> Yeah.
Right, that looks like something.
>> Yeah, it's really hard to
hard to tell. It's been down there a
long time, whatever it is.
>> Looks like a section of a engine. That
looks nice.
Got cables there, have you?
That looked like the framework of a of a
wing or something.
>> They'd stumbled upon a
once-in-a-lifetime discovery.
A World War II bomber known as a Fairey
Barracuda
that appeared to be completely intact.
The Barracuda was designed by British
company Fairey Aviation.
It was built as a torpedo dive bomber,
the first of its kind made entirely from
metal.
It could carry a variety of deadly
payloads from six 250 lb bombs to a 450
lb depth charge or a huge 1,600 lb
torpedo.
The Barracuda made its maiden flight in
December 1940 and was operated by the
Royal Navy's Fleet Air Arm.
At the discovery site under the Solent,
a team from Wessex Archaeology have been
brought in to try to raise this
extraordinary plane from the sea floor.
>> The aircraft is buried in a buttery type
mud, which is not easy when it comes to
excavation.
Above the seabed, very little remains.
But as we are excavating down, more and
more is becoming open to us.
>> More than 2,600 Barracudas were built,
but not a single complete plane survives
today.
Dave Morris from the Fleet Air Arm
Museum in Somerset is heading up an
ambitious project to reconstruct an
entire Barracuda using salvaged parts.
>> We have
crash site remains from a number of
Barracudas which have been recovered
over more than 40 years of collecting
now,
but they've all been subject to, you
know,
very fast collisions to high ground
mountains. So, this is the first time
that we've come across a Barracuda which
is largely still intact and in in most
of its original shape.
>> It will be a dream come true for Dave's
rebuild project if the plane can be
raised in one piece.
>> It's pretty amazing. You descend down
the shot line and you see the remains of
the Rolls-Royce Merlin engine that is
quite prominent on the seabed. As you go
further back, there what remains of the
fuselage, the cockpit, and the wings are
still in place.
>> Records note that a Barracuda took off
on the 6th of January, 1944,
from HMS Daedalus, which is now the
nearby Lee-on-the-Solent airfield.
It suffered engine failure and pitched
into the sea. The pilot managed to bail
out and survived the crash.
>> We know that it was a a fairly smooth
belly landing rather than a than a
violent crash. We know the pilot escaped
okay. Um so, there's a lot of
information we're putting together from
records and also matching that against
the evidence that we're finding on on
the seabed now.
>> Before the plane can be raised, a
powerful underwater siphon pump is used
to suck the mud out from around the
fuselage and wings.
But, working out how to raise the plane
intact is proving to be a significant
challenge.
The divers realize the frame is much
more fragile than they previously
thought.
The mud is tightly packed into the
individual component parts, making the
plane very heavy and likely to break up
on lifting.
>> We're going to have to dismantle the
aircraft underwater because,
unfortunately, it's too fragile to bring
up in one piece.
>> Despite the setback, the divers have
managed to isolate a large part of one
of the wings and are carefully preparing
it for lifting.
Slowly, the unbroken wing piece is
brought up from the seafloor.
Once out of the water, the team need to
work quickly.
>> It starts to decay as soon as it comes
out.
It's been in the sea for 75 years or so.
When you are trying to conserve our
critical material, you want to try and
keep it in the same conditions as to how
it's been
What we're going to do is wrap it up and
then keep it at least
wet, damp to try and stop the corrosion
continuing.
>> The plane hasn't come up in one piece,
but as more parts are slowly brought to
the surface, Dave Morris is optimistic.
>> Absolutely amazed to see obviously a
piece of the Barracuda coming up after
76 years.
Yeah, you can still tap on the aluminum.
I expected it to be a lot more
corroded
considering it's been down there for so
many years.
>> Later on, we'll be following the
recovered parts of the plane, which will
be taken to the Fleet Air Arm Museum.
For now, Dave still has high hopes he
can use these parts to help complete his
reconstruction of this long-forgotten
plane.
Our next dig is in the Lake District,
where archaeologists are excavating the
site of a very special hostel. It was a
temporary home for hundreds of children
who were rescued from concentration
camps in Nazi-occupied Europe and
brought to Britain to start a new life.
On the shore of Lake Windermere, in the
heart of the Lake District, is the
village of Troutbeck Bridge.
The archaeologists here are hoping to
shed light on an incredible wartime
story of survival against the odds.
>> The Holocaust isn't just something
[music] that happened in Eastern Europe.
We have sites related to the Holocaust
here on British shores. So, this is one
of them. We're excavating the remains of
what we think is [music] um a hostel
where Jewish children were brought at
the end of the war.
>> The dig is organized by the Lake
District Holocaust Project.
It aims to remember the special role
this area played in helping to
rehabilitate children liberated from
Nazi concentration camps at the end of
the war.
Two boys that came here in 1945 were Ike
Altman
and Sam Laskier.
>> That's me.
A cheerful little fellow.
>> Life in Poland for these Jewish boys
changed dramatically the moment Germany
invaded in September 1939.
>> We were lined up.
The assessment came and started
counting.
Father was in front
and I was behind him.
And he said to me, "Stand on your tiptoe
to make you look a bit taller than you
are."
Next to him was my mother,
my sister, my little brother.
"All those on the right, stay where you
are.
All those on the left,
march out."
Through the front of the square there.
That's my mother, my little brother,
sister.
Never to be seen [music] again.
>> Both boys were sent to a succession of
concentration camps before ending up in
Auschwitz-Birkenau.
>> You had a number
tattooed.
See, that was tattooed to me in
Birkenau.
>> But then in May 1945, the boys were
finally liberated from a camp in
Czechoslovakia. [music]
>> We were in the barrack. We didn't know
what was going on.
But suddenly, we looked around
and there were no guards.
They just
disappeared.
And that is the moment I realized
we were free.
I am the one
waving
his hat.
Everybody so happy. [music] We're alive.
We're alive. We couldn't believe.
>> On the 13th of August, they were flown
from Prague and brought by bus up to
Windermere.
>> Well, I knew wherever they're taking me,
it's got to be much better wherever I
was.
>> The boys were housed in one of three
hostels located on what was the Calgarth
estate, a town that had been built
during the war to house workers from the
nearby Sunderland Flying Boat Factory.
After the war, the town was demolished
and a school was built here.
This is the first time the site has been
excavated.
The team are hoping to find evidence of
one of the hostel buildings in the hope
that they can learn something about the
lives of the children that were brought
here.
>> We're finding huge amounts uh still
exist within the ground. So, that
includes sort of types of material that
the structures were made from. So, we're
finding bricks and concrete and mortar.
We're finding things like window glass.
>> 300 orphaned Jewish children were
brought to the Lake District. They were
known as the Windermere boys.
>> Many of the children who came here had
been in Bergen-Belsen. [music]
Um some of them had been in Auschwitz,
but other slave labor camps, forced
labor camps,
um in ghettos across Europe. So, for
many, many years they'd experienced
terrible, terrible atrocities. [music]
They were very much alone. They didn't
know how many of [music] their family
members survived.
>> But not all of the Windermere boys were
actually boys. In fact, 28 of them were
girls.
Denise's mother, Minia, was one of them.
>> My mom was very proud to be one of the
boys.
Although they were in the minority
because they made a fuss of the girls as
well.
They had plenty of boys to choose from.
Denise has been helping out with the
dig. We found lots of pieces of tiles
and water pipes
or sewage pipes. We were thinking that
it's probably some kind of bathroom. I
was thinking my mom must have had to
work in the bathroom
>> [laughter]
>> over there.
The team are finding lots of evidence of
the hostel building, but precious few
personal items.
>> One of the objects that we found, quite
a a poignant one we think and it's a
little tiny plastic
unicorn um which may or may not have
been um as a pendant around somebody's
neck.
So, this looks to be really interesting
find of a small penknife.
Um
looks like it's made of mother of pearl,
but it's so corroded that the blade
can't actually come out. It's the kind
of thing that, you know, a child would
have had and really looked after and
carried around with them everywhere.
>> It may have been more than 70 years ago,
but Sam and [music] Ike's memories of
arriving in Windermere are still vivid.
>> It's very nice at night, so we didn't do
much. The following morning, you see the
hills and the lake. We were we had our
place near the lakes as well.
And we thought this is paradise.
>> This is the main hall.
That's me.
Over here.
There was beds, clean sheets, pillow
cases.
We would run outside, you know, we
didn't have any proper things to wear.
Some went out in their underpants and
we were wild. We were wild.
It was the most fantastic feeling.
>> Although the rescued children only lived
here for 6 months, it was a
life-changing experience.
They were offered counseling and
schooling including English lessons
before being resettled elsewhere in the
UK.
>> It is a very positive story of hope in a
in a terrible time of despair and I
think it's really important to to
humanize
um stories of of refugees.
>> Today Ican and Sam have come back to the
village as they're keen to see the
excavation.
>> It is very important and it's very
important [music] that we also tell
people what it was like.
Although a lot of things have changed
but we kept the memories.
>> The dig has helped local residents
reconnect with this unique and important
time in their village's history.
>> Archaeology speaks to people in a
special kind of way and
>> [music]
>> I think we owe that the the survivors
and the children
the chance to you know put their story
out there and I think that's what
archaeology can do.
>> I've invited Kevin to come and tell me
more about the project.
Kevin, you've been digging in the Lake
District but your your usual work
focusing on the Holocaust takes you over
to to Eastern Europe. So this is this is
a very different kind of dig for you.
>> Yeah, absolutely. We do a lot in in
Eastern Europe looking at the
archaeology of what happened during the
Holocaust takes us to
Poland and and Ukraine and those sort of
areas but this project gave us the
opportunity to do something a little bit
closer to home.
>> And you did find a selection of of quite
personal objects. So I think I think
this one really stands out for me, this
little horse.
>> So we're not sure whether it's a horse
or a unicorn. I think it's a unicorn or
it's
an important object. It dates to around
late 30s, 40s, so it's the right sort of
period with a unicorn being
a mythical creature associated with hope
and magic.
To find that on the site where we were
looking for evidence of what these boys
went through and how they lived their
life in Windermere, then that was a
perfect start for us actually to find
that.
>> Is it a little pendant?
>> A little pendant, yeah. Wear around the
neck.
>> Yeah. What I find really kind of moving
about this is that, you know, that might
be something that I dig up in my garden
at home and it and it has very little
meaning attached to it. In this context
>> Absolutely.
>> it comes with all that meaning.
>> And then uh
>> What's that? The tube.
>> Interesting. Curly top. So, it's a hair
curling gel, but it's made for toddlers
and babies.
>> Yes, it says for toddlers.
>> For toddlers.
>> Curly top.
>> So, it's to make your baby's hair grow
curly.
>> The natural hair curler.
>> Mhm.
>> For toddlers.
>> So, it would have been a culture shock
to these children to all of a sudden be
in an environment where
you could curl your baby's hair using a
gel.
>> And then
what about this buckle?
>> Quite important. It's it's a belt
buckle. It's quite
common to the period. So, we're talking
sort of 1930s, 1940s right through to
the 50s. Could well be that this
belonged to to one of them.
>> What else have you got? There's a
There's a bottle top.
>> Yeah, Veno's, isn't it?
That is a cough medicine. It just
demonstrates that these children went
from having no medical care whatsoever
to all of a sudden to find themselves in
a place where if they got a cough
they would be given some Veno's cough
medicine by a nurse or a doctor.
>> Yeah.
>> Um it just demonstrates how dramatically
their life changed overnight.
>> Yeah.
And the care that was suddenly around
them.
>> Absolutely.
>> Do you think finding objects like this,
does it make it feel as though that time
is more distant or or closer to the
present day when you find these objects?
>> The sort of argument here is that
why do we do archaeology on such a
recent period?
Because we already know the answers cuz
we've got books and photographs and all
sorts of things.
But actually I think it's important cuz
archaeologists look at evidence and data
in a slightly different way.
>> Yeah.
>> So we we are asking new questions of
these archive documents and these data.
So actually we can present new evidence
and that's what this project is all
about. It's bringing to the forefront
this little section of Windermere in the
1940s just to see what the life was like
for these people.
>> We now turn our attention to another
group of people who came to Britain
during the war.
In the build-up to D-Day, military camps
sprung up right across the country.
As well as housing British soldiers,
[music]
these sites were home to thousands of
Canadian and American troops.
Our next dig comes from Salisbury where
a team of British ex-military personnel
are hoping to find the remains of a
barracks used by the second battalion of
the US Army's 506th Parachute Infantry
Regiment, otherwise known as Easy
Company.
The men of this elite American [music]
parachute unit also came to be known as
the Band of Brothers.
They came to Britain in September 1943
and remained here for 9 months preparing
alongside other Allied troops
for the D-Day invasion.
Their training camp was located near the
village of Aldbourne in Wiltshire.
MOD archaeologist Richard Osgood is on
site with members of Operation
Nightingale. This is an initiative using
archaeology to support the recovery of
military personnel injured in conflict.
>> On the surface you can see nothing. This
is just a a sports pitch. What we wanted
to do to see if archaeology could tell
us anything about what lies below the
surface and link us to those men from
Easy Company and take us back to those
days of D-Day.
>> We know from military photographs that
in 1943 and '44, [music] this field
housed a number of wooden barracks.
This was the first time these young
soldiers had left their base in America.
>> Some of them described it as the best
accommodation they had in the whole war.
And others said they felt that they were
on a Hollywood film set because this
village is so beautiful.
>> But the paratroopers would soon leave
this quaint Wiltshire village far
behind.
In the early hours of the 6th of June,
1944, the men of Easy Company were
dropped behind enemy lines in Normandy.
Their mission to seize key bridges and
clear routes leading away from Utah
Beach to allow safe passage of US ground
troops who would arrive by sea just a
few hours later. The plan went awry with
many missing their drop zone.
But they still managed [music] to
capture and destroy four German field
guns, saving countless Allied lives.
Easy Company went on to become one of
the best-known Allied fighting forces in
the war,
even making it all the way to Hitler's
mountain top retreat in the Bavarian
Alps.
Back at the dig, the team are hoping to
find some personal items.
They want to gain a glimpse into the
lives of these soldiers when they were
stationed here during the weeks leading
up to the D-Day invasion.
>> One of the really exciting bits about
archaeology is when you're able to put
yourselves literally in the footsteps of
people that did incredible deeds in the
past.
>> Already they're finding telltale
structures just beneath the surface.
>> Not many people get excited by concrete
necessarily, especially 20th century
concrete, but we've got 1 2 3 4 pads of
a building that were put into this field
in the 1940s. And this is the remnants
of the platoon sergeant's building.
What have you got there?
>> Uh it looks like some sort of
iron cooking pot
possibly.
It's a coin. It's a uh
halfpenny.
>> They're also finding artifacts that
directly link to Easy Company's pivotal
role on D-Day.
>> Just pulled this out of the ground and
didn't have a clue what it was, but we
borrowed Paul's book and we found out
exactly what it was.
It's the the handle for the emergency uh
parachutes.
>> Yeah.
>> Oh my fantastic.
>> There are even finds that don't often
survive being buried.
>> Our military expert has now identified
this as being
parachute silk. You're standing in a hut
used by Easy Company, and you're
touching parachute silk used by those
paratroopers.
>> And that that is amazing.
>> It's as good as a link to D-Day as
you're ever going to get.
>> Eagerly sought personal items are also
surfacing. They're helping to paint a
picture of life outside of combat
training.
>> This is a fairly fun piece of evidence.
It's a bottle of Brylcreem that they'd
have put in their hair to make
themselves look presentable having had
their their training and got themselves
ready for an evening out.
One of the local buildings was a place
where the Americans did a lot of their
dancing with the local girls.
The story goes that they they made such
good use of that venue that at the end
of the war they had to pay for the floor
to be re-laid.
The hall still [music] exists today. The
floor's in really good condition.
>> The dig is giving a unique insight into
the reality of daily life for these
brave men just at that moment before
they left Britain for D-Day in June
1944.
>> This particular room, and I'm just
standing by the entrance looking into
the hut,
is their last moment of quiet, peace,
tranquility, and probably a great deal
of reflection before they dropped in on
Normandy.
And that
adds a real element of pathos, I think,
to this particular site.
>> I've asked Richard to bring in some of
those personal items for a closer
>> look.
And you've got some of the finds here
from inside the hut, including that,
which is extraordinary.
>> I I you know, the hairs on the back of
my neck when you find something like
this,
and we're talking paratroopers. This is
a handle of a reserve parachute used by
somebody in Easy Company.
>> So, that's for your backup parachute.
>> That's right. Your first parachute is a
what's called a static line. It's pulled
by the aircraft itself, and it opens up,
and you parachute down, hopefully. And
if that doesn't work, you've got that to
keep you alive.
>> And you've got some smaller objects. So,
you talk me through these.
What have we got here? Um a badge?
>> Well, that's a little touch of them
being very human, in fact. It's a
basketball supporter's badge.
>> Let's get it under there. So, there's a
little basketball on there.
>> That's right. It says, "I support." But,
tantalizingly, we don't know who this
individual soldier supported. So, you've
got you've got a little trace of of them
being keen on life back home, but just
whom we don't know.
>> And this looks like something which
you'd find on the head of a guitar.
>> I think it's a mandolin.
>> You're right.
>> They're
passing time playing playing musical
instruments, one of the ways that they
kept themselves occupied in in the
evenings.
>> And what's this?
>> That is a nylon stocking found in the
hut.
>> Hm.
>> Um I don't know how far we go into that
Maybe maybe there's some chap who used a
lot of Brylcreem and um had done pretty
well on his dancing skills.
>> Had a small gift with him.
>> There were numerous um histories and
anecdotes of the guys uh giving kids
sweets and um and chewing gum, things
like that, and luxuries like these these
uh these stockings. So, it's all part of
that liaising with the locals and and
getting them on side. It's a nice
tantalizing touch again that this
soldier might have had um maybe happier
things happening before they went to to
D-Day.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
And it is it is like we're looking at a
little American colony in 1940s Britain.
>> That's right. We've got one small
trench, but it's giving us loads of
finds relating to a a pivotal moment in
history and a really famous group of of
young men. Um and it is about Americana,
it's about what they're doing to fight,
what they're doing to try and stay
human, and it's just a small keyhole
into those days of 1943 and 1944. And as
such, I think it's actually quite quite
a fascinating little collection of
finds.
>> And I think what's interesting, too, is
that you're you're digging with
veterans who are bringing their own
experiences to bear on the archaeology
they're uncovering.
>> Completely. We had um
several um British military guys with us
who have have faced combat, so they know
the sorts of experiences and traumas
that these these men have faced. And for
them, that was a really important and
powerful thing, cuz they could directly
connect to the men of Easy Company,
albeit from a 21st century perspective.
>> Yeah.
>> Um and therefore, finding this sort of
thing for them was was quite an
emotional experience, I think.
>> We now return to the raising of the
Fairey Barracuda bomber from the murky
waters just off the South Coast. All of
the parts that were recovered have now
been transferred to the Fleet Air Arm
Museum in Somerset, and our raving
archaeologist Nisha McSweeney is there
to see how the team is attempting to
reconstruct this long-forgotten bomber.
The discovery of an intact Barracuda
bomber was a world's first, but sadly
the salvage team could not raise it in
one piece and had to bring it up in
parts.
At the Fleet Air Arm Museum, Dave Morris
is head of an ambitious project to
rebuild a whole Barracuda using only
original parts.
For the last 40 years, they've been
collecting fragments salvaged from
various crash sites.
But these are very difficult to use in
the rebuild because they're so battered
and mangled. [music]
This could all be about to change with
the treasure trove of parts raised over
several days from the Solent.
>> So Dave, where are we so far with the
with the project putting this giant
multiple jigsaw pieces back together?
>> If you were to look at
basically the plan form of a Barracuda
and and think, "Okay, let's build one of
those." I think you would stop on day
one. It would just become too
mind-boggling.
>> Chief engineer William Gibbs has been
working on the project for 5 years.
He has to identify each specific part,
then work out where they go. It's a
complex process.
>> So we might put something together and
then it has to come apart again.
>> Okay.
>> Um which is which is annoying, but it's
just part of the process.
>> So far, he's rebuilt the cockpit.
>> So just help me visualize this a bit
more. You've got the pilot sitting here.
You've got the wings over here. This is
the nose of the airplane going behind
us?
>> The engine, yes. The engine The engine
would fit in front there, in front of
the pilot. So we've got the engine and
propeller there, and then the remainder
of the aircraft and the tail would be 30
or so feet down in that direction. So
she's a big airplane.
>> It's It This is a huge plane.
>> The project is already providing a
glimpse into the working lives of the
people who built these planes more than
70 years ago.
>> On here, we've got
drawings, pencil drawings done in the
factory. We were the first people to see
those drawings since they were doodled
on in the Boulton and Paul factory in
the factory.
Pretty poor factory
um
behavior. You shouldn't go scribbling
and doodling on airplanes, but this was
wartime Great Britain and there was a
little bit of camaraderie and morale
going on.
>> Dave is now pinning his hopes on
sections of the Barracuda raised from
the Solent providing a mountain of
usable parts to help complete the build.
>> We started finding there were hundreds
of really valuable fittings, tube ends,
constructional details, components for
the Barracuda that we could harvest.
You can't even begin to measure how
useful this is for the project.
>> As well as large sections such as a
fuselage and the wing piece outside the
hangar, individual parts harvested from
the Solent wreck are undergoing chemical
preservation.
So, what what have you got in these
tanks?
What's the magic solution that's getting
rid of all this gunk?
>> This is
just ordinary fresh water, tap water
mixed with uh citric acid.
>> The citric acid helps reduce the
alkalinity of the sea water
producing a more neutral pH solution.
This helps to stabilize the parts and
reduce any further degradation.
See what we got?
>> Yeah.
>> Oh, okay.
>> It's a pipe, but a collecting pipe, and
then we've got
>> Ooh, yuck.
>> And the rubber is incredibly supple.
>> The rubber?
>> Yeah. Oh, yeah.
>> Oh, this one does not smell good.
There's a long way to go before all the
components salvaged from the Solent
wreck will be ready for use in the
reconstruction of the plane.
But Dave has already made some
astonishing discoveries.
>> These are a pair of batteries from the
Solent wreck, two 12-V batteries dated
June '43. We couldn't resist putting
a tester on the batteries and one of
them
still has 0.86
residual volts of current in it. It's
absolutely remarkable that 76 years on
the seabed. Absolutely.
So, we are there are some remarkable
quirky little finds coming up from from
the Solent wreck.
>> I don't think I've ever seen a a
conservation challenge quite like this
one. I'm used to working out on site
with conservators to put together
ancient pottery or other kinds of
artifacts. And and that that's extremely
difficult to do, but this
this is something on a different scale.
Right? The the complexity of it is just
ramped up hugely.
>> The rebuild project has many years of
work ahead, but Dave is now confident
that with the Solent wreck, one day he
will be able to wheel out complete
Barracuda, the very last of its kind.
>> We now move from British planes to
German military hardware.
One of the most destructive weapons
developed by Nazi Germany was the V2
rocket, the forerunner to later
ballistic missiles.
Each rocket bore a warhead containing
900 kg of explosives, and it's thought
that around 3,000 rockets were launched
at Allied targets during the Second
[music] World War.
We now join two brothers who are on the
search for a V2 rocket which fortunately
never hit its target and ended up in a
farmer's field.
The hunt is focused near the village of
Marden in Kent.
Amateur military archaeologists Colin
and Shawn Welsh are on the trail of a V2
that struck here at 2:15 a.m. on the 9th
of March, 1945.
Aerial imagery taken after the war shows
it came down in this field.
>> We've excavated several
V2 rockets and V1 flying bombs. So, um
I'm afraid to say we've become experts.
>> The V2 was the forerunner to rockets
that would eventually put a man on the
moon.
It was invented in Germany in the 1930s
and later developed as an explosive
[music]
missile by the Nazis.
The key to its long range was the
innovation of using liquid oxygen and
alcohol to propel the rocket.
At the dig in Kent, the brothers hope
that the remains of the rocket could
reveal clues to its trajectory and how
it detonated.
To help locate the impact site, they use
a portable magnetometer.
>> If there are large steel parts in the
grounds,
that will then cause a disturbance to
the uh magnetic uh orientation in the
ground.
The magnetometer will detect that and
give us a signal.
>> Using the survey results, they map out
what they believe is the extent of the
impact crater now buried underground.
And they start to dig.
Just a meter down and they're already
finding indirect evidence of [music] the
detonation.
>> There was an orchard here and obviously
the trees were destroyed and the damaged
trees were pushed back into the hole and
buried with the infill. And the one that
you can see standing up just there,
that's got a broken off top
which would have been caused by the
blast of the device.
>> Strong magnetometer readings down in the
hole indicates they're still on target.
The heavy clay soil makes it difficult
to locate small finds, but it does have
its benefits.
>> This is the tiniest little [music] bit
here, and the aluminum
looks almost fresh in the find, and
that's because of the absence of oxygen
in the hole. That's a good sign. It
means that any future finds are going to
be, hopefully, in a good state of
preservation.
>> The V2 had a maximum range of 320 km and
traveled at over 1,000 m per second.
>> It was traveling so fast that you could
be stood at this spot and not know that
a V2 was approaching.
You wouldn't see it coming. You wouldn't
hear it coming.
>> Launched at Britain from sites in the
Nazi-controlled Netherlands, the V2s
caused an estimated 9,000 British
civilian and military deaths.
As the brothers dig deeper, recognizable
pieces of the rocket are now starting to
emerge.
>> This is one of the support brackets
for either the oxygen tank or the
alcohol tank.
That's quite a nice find. Let's just see
what my brother concurs.
All right. Well, I know what it is. But
that's one of the uh
clamps for the fuel tanks. I just
I just said that I'd get you to confirm
it with me. Okay. So, you haven't told
Well, you
>> I told him just now.
>> Okay. Well, I'll come down again. Show
what a pair of nerds we are that we know
every bit of a V2 rocket.
>> [laughter]
>> Should be nearby. There's something
>> Deeper still, and key parts of the
supersonic engine are coming to light.
>> It doesn't look like very much at the
moment, but this is a burner cup from
the combustion chamber of the V2 rocket.
I can tell that it's a burner cup
because of that little bit of brass
there,
which was an injector nozzle. So,
alcohol was pushed through that to
squirt a feed into the combustion
chamber. There were 18 of these, and
this is the first one out of our
excavation.
>> I don't see my side panel. That's 3.1.
>> 3.1.
>> As the excavation continues, the
brothers make an intriguing discovery
linked to the precise moment of impact.
>> When we look down in there, we can see
that the clay itself has changed color
rather than the nice bright yellow
orange in the surrounds.
It's a horrible uh gray color, which I
think is due to the uh carbonization of
the uh the materials.
The V2 was exploding as it traveled into
the ground at three times the speed of
sound.
The detonation couldn't keep up with how
fast it was traveling, so it got in at
least 5 ft into the ground
before it actually detonated.
>> This is a fascinating revelation.
>> The original intention was to try and
create something like a blast weapon on
the surface.
What they didn't bargain for, the
supersonic speed took the rocket
further into soft ground than they might
have expected.
>> This V2 rocket had clearly gone off
target when it hit the field.
And it only detonated once it had
penetrated the ground.
The blast from its warhead would have
been absorbed by the clay.
6 m down, the brothers finally reach the
bottom of the impact crater.
The plan now is to clean and preserve
the finds and scan them to create a
digital archive.
>> I quite enjoy
the physics of the the excavation.
I particularly enjoy
building a representation of what it was
that happened at the site. We found a
lot about the geology and what it does
to the finds.
I think we've done pretty well.
>> Colin and Shawn's excavation is part of
an ongoing investigation into the role
this terrifying weapon had on Britain
during the war.
Prior to D-Day in June 1944, the Allied
forces staged a number of rehearsals of
the landings, all in top secret. One of
these was called Operation Tiger and it
would end in absolute tragedy. But,
because of the secrecy, very few people
knew about it.
Then, in the 1970s, one man uncovered
evidence of the event and fought to
bring the story to light. Nisha
McSweeney met his son.
>> The incident took place off the Devon
coast near Slapton [music]
Sands.
Operation Tiger may have remained a
forgotten moment in history if it wasn't
for the amateur archaeological sleuthing
of a local man named Ken Small.
I'm meeting his son, Dean, to find out
more.
>> When did your father first begin to
suspect that there was something out
there?
>> He was beachcombing and he came across
things like tunic buttons,
empty shell cases,
identity bracelets, various various
parts of identity All these bits, knives
and forks, spoons, parts of them. And he
thought, "Well, this is weird. Why would
this be on a beach?"
>> A local fisherman added to the mystery.
He told Ken about a spot just out from
the beach where their nets would snag on
something large underwater.
In the summer of 1974, Ken persuaded a
diver friend to go down and take a look.
>> My dad took him out in a the
He dived down. He came up and he said to
my dad, "It's a tank." And my dad said,
"Well, what? An oil tank? Water tank?"
He said, "No, it's like an army tank."
And my dad just thought, "This is crazy.
How can this be?"
>> Ken started to search local records and
military archives for answers. It was
then that he stumbled across a wartime
exercise code-named Operation Tiger.
Operation Tiger was carried out in April
1944.
It was one of a number of practice
exercises involving troops from Britain,
the US, and Canada that all took place
in preparation for the Normandy
landings.
30,000 US troops were sent to Slapton
Sands to rehearse their part in D-Day.
>> All of this stuff was completely covered
up. So, there was very little evidence
as to what went on, the the actual
exercises themselves.
>> Determined to find out more about the
tank, in May 1984, Ken took amateur
maritime archaeology to a new level.
With the help of friends and local
divers, he raised the tank off the
seafloor.
>> They got a big bulldozer, they strapped
a cable to it, and they started to pull
it along the concrete slipway, and
amazingly, the tracks started to turn.
[music]
>> It's incredible.
>> Yeah. And then all the crustacea and
stuff that had grown on the tank over
years of being under the water all
started to break away and crumble off,
and you can actually see grease still on
the thing. It's just amazing.
>> The tank was immediately jet cleaned and
sprayed with rust preventer to protect
it from decay.
>> So, this is it.
>> This is the tank.
>> It's enormous.
It's amazing to think about this under
the water, and of course they were
snagging their nets and all.
>> Yeah.
>> Dean, this is crazy for me. So, I'm used
to when I when I dig up, you know, iron
objects from the Iron Age, they come up
as like really crusty, corroded things.
It's hard to tell what they are, but
this is in fabulous condition.
>> Ken had recovered an American amphibious
Sherman DD tank.
So, what happens is all around the tank
[music] there's this flotation collar,
and it's raised with compressed air
upwards, and it forms a complete skirt
around the tank.
>> Fantastic. So, this is a fully
amphibious tank, tank boat, tank.
>> While the DD tank was ahead of its time,
it could be quite unreliable.
Several of them, including the one Ken
raised off the seafloor, were known to
have sunk during the D-Day rehearsals
due to mechanical faults.
But as Ken investigated further, he
discovered that Operation Tiger wasn't
just blighted by technical problems.
Something far more deadly had occurred.
By early 1944, the Germans knew Allied
forces were planning to invade
Nazi-controlled France.
They just weren't sure where or when.
By listening in to the Allied radio
chatter, they got wind of Operation
Tiger.
On the 28th of April, 1944, nine German
E-boats were sent out on patrol and
headed for the coast of Devon.
Armed with torpedoes, these were highly
maneuverable, deadly attack craft.
That night, Allied ships taking part in
Operation Tiger came under attack. Two
US tank landing ships were sunk, and
three more badly damaged. More than 700
US servicemen drowned or died of
hypothermia as they waited to be
rescued.
In 2012, two wartime shipwrecks known to
lie off the Devon coast were formally
identified as the two tank landing ships
or LSTs that were sunk during Operation
Tiger.
As part of a project to grant the wrecks
special status, maritime archaeologist
Graham Scott is heading out to survey
them.
>> What's really important about these
wrecks is that they're associated with
D-Day and they're associated with
practices for D-Day.
Historic England have asked
us to investigate these wrecks for them
and to advise them what's left of them
and how important they are.
>> Now anchored over the wrecks, they
prepare to send down a remotely operated
vehicle or ROV.
Equipped with sonar and specialist
low-light cameras, the team can stream a
live feed from 50 m down direct to the
control room.
>> Okay, mate. That's us. We got a visual.
We'll just work out what we're doing.
>> Yeah, Roger that.
>> Let's orientate ourselves and let's move
along to the west.
>> Today, Graham is concentrating on one of
the ships. He wants to assess what state
it's in, what equipment it was carrying,
and any potentially live munitions still
on board.
>> We are wondering whether we have found a
gun here.
We are rather hoping that this is
evidence of the ship's armaments.
We could be wrong.
>> You start tethering easy. Tethering
easy.
>> Roger that.
>> One thing we have to be careful with on
a wreck like this is the
uh presence of ammunition.
We don't touch any of that. We uh back
the ROV away to a safe distance. We've
no real idea
whether these things are still viable.
We've got to treat them as
uh
as though they could still potentially
uh explode if we blunder into them.
>> Moving along the boat, the ROV camera
captures a lifeboat crane,
a cargo net,
and the engine.
>> The hull is upside down. These were very
shallow drafted vessels and they tended
to capsize when they sank.
>> We now know that on the night of the
attack, chaos ensued.
>> The men on board the landing ships
thought that the firing initially was
part of the exercise.
And it was only when one of the ships
was torpedoed and they saw this
>> [music]
>> massive explosion that they realized
they were actually under attack. And
then all hell breaks loose.
Everybody starts firing everywhere, very
confusing.
>> Following the deadly Nazi attack, the
Operation Tiger disaster was quickly
covered up.
It remained largely unknown for decades
until Ken Small found and raised his
tank. While the tank was not sunk in the
enemy attack, it now stands as a
permanent memorial to all the US
servicemen who lost their lives during
the D-Day rehearsal.
Ken Small Dean still has his father's
collection of artifacts.
>> Okay.
These didn't come out of the tank.
>> Yeah, they did. Yeah, they they they
Yeah, they did. This one here is is a
rangefinder and this, I believe, is is
used to work out the elevation
for the main gun, the main gun at the
main gun in the turret of the tank.
>> Yeah, line of fire.
>> Line of fire, yeah.
>> In recognition of Ken's determination to
bring the story of Operation Tiger to
light and remember the American soldiers
who lost their lives.
He received a letter of gratitude from
the president.
>> Dear Mr. Small,
>> Yes.
>> on behalf of all Americans, thank you
for your kind and generous efforts.
Sincerely, Ronald Reagan.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> I think it's a really important story
that deserves to be much more widely
told. I mean, it's it's a big kind of
part of um prepare the preparations for
D-Day, which we just hadn't heard about.
It took someone like Ken to to get that
story out there and and to give those
people who died and their families and
the survivors um a voice and something
to kind of remember it by.
During the war, Northern Ireland had 28
airfields home to both RAF and US Army
Air Force crews.
Whether through combat damage,
mechanical failure, or pilot error, not
every plane returned home.
For our final dig, a team of
archaeologists has been joined by an
army of volunteer [music] school
children from both sides of the Irish
border, and they are excavating the site
of a crashed American fighter plane.
On December the 17th, 1942,
22-year-old American pilot Second
Lieutenant Milo Rundel was returning to
the Royal Naval Air Station at Eglinton
when he went off course.
As part of an ongoing project to
highlight the role played by Northern
Ireland during the war, aviation
historian Johnny McNee has been trying
to find Rundel's plane.
>> We have eyewitnesses said a plane
crashed in this direction. What we're
trying to work out from the archaeology
is that correct? Uh Uh and the
orientation of the aircraft and did it
go in vertically? Did it sort of bounce
across the field and then suddenly bury
itself under a corner?
>> Rundell parachuted safely down into
Northern Ireland and returned to base.
But his plane hit the ground somewhere
near the town of Clough Blaney in County
Monaghan, just south of the border in
Ireland. While parts of the plane were
recovered at the time of the crash, it
hit the ground so hard that much of it
still lies buried.
>> We're fairly sure that these are engine
parts, lots of cables, clamps, ducts,
bits of very contorted and smashed up
metal work with a distinct aroma of fuel
off it.
>> It looks to be part of the outside we're
standing in because it has that greenish
paint on it.
>> Not Not 100% sure.
Uh we have a long hinged object here.
Could be a door, could be
It's very light material.
>> Records reveal that Lieutenant Rundell
was flying a US fighter plane known as a
Lockheed P-38 Lightning.
The P-38 was the first fighter aircraft
to fly faster than 400 mph.
With its four nose-mounted machine guns
and 20-mil cannon, it was feared by
Allied enemies.
The Japanese called it two planes, one
pilot because of its unusual design. The
Germans knew it as the fork-tailed
devil.
Back at the dig, Johnny is now finding
clues that can be traced back to where
the plane was manufactured.
>> We're finding lots of these little fuel
clamps.
And these clamps hold, you know, the
insulation and rubber tubing around
various parts. You can see the
manufacturer the patent number, so it's
Wittek Manufacturing Company, Chicago,
USA. And even look at that.
Still threaded, still working.
>> We know that Wittek's made fuel clamps
for the P-38, so the team are definitely
digging in the right place.
Johnny is now recognizing other specific
parts of the plane.
>> That's a serious bit of sheet steel.
That must be
5 6 7 mil thick, you know, so it's it's
not like aluminum. It's there for a
purpose, and that purpose would be to
stop bullets hitting the pilot or the
engine components.
>> Confident they have found Rendall's P-38
Lightning, the layout and condition of
the wreckage is also providing clues as
to how it crashed.
>> The debris that we're getting here
suggests that the aircraft did enter the
ground almost uh I would say at about a
70 80° angle into the ground.
So, you've got to imagine the iconic
design, two engines,
without a pilot, roaring from across the
sky,
running low on fuel from the west, it's
come in almost vertical into our stony
field,
>> [music]
>> and this iconic design has been turned
in a matter of seconds
into this crumpled pile of metal that
you can see.
>> For the school children volunteers, the
dig is giving them a tangible connection
to the brave young pilots that were
based near here almost 80 years ago.
>> So, it helps bring history to life. So,
it's [music] like relating the artifacts
to what we're learning, and we can see
really like what happened and how it
would have like looked in our type of
perspective.
>> I've asked Johnny to bring in some of
the finds to see what else we can learn
about this plane and its pilot.
>> So, what have we got here then? Where
where do these parts belong to on on the
Lightning?
>> You've got little inlet exhaust valves
from the engine. Broken bits of the
cockpit that locks the the the cockpit
latches down when you shut it and go
flying. But, you can see the little
serrated
buttons here just for locking your
cockpit.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh closed. We have some of the Perspex
still with the distinct wartime olive
drab paint
>> Yeah.
>> on it.
Um and some of the very fearsome nose
armament
was also recovered. So, we have two
50-calibre bullets.
There are four 50-calibre Browning
machine guns on the front, plus a 20-mm
uh
cannon.
>> And then there's a a plate here.
>> Yes, that was one of the the star finds
by the pupils. I mean, they really were
forensically going through the soil. And
one of them said, "Oh, I've got a little
plate with writing on it."
And you can see there
all the drawing information, the
contract, the date, tells you the oil
capacity, and then right at the bottom,
Lockheed Aviation Corp. So, that 100%
proves that we were dealing with the
crash of a Lockheed P-38. That was a
good find.
>> And what on earth are these?
>> They came out, if you can imagine, in
our profile with engine wreckage,
cockpit wreckage, and engine wreckage.
And these were in the cockpit.
And there was a lot of head-scratching
amongst the team. You know, people were
suggesting they were like butter paddles
or they were something agricultural.
>> Yeah.
>> Um and we put some articles into the
P-38 Association magazine in America and
said, "Does anybody know what these are
before we make some grand announcement
and look stupid?"
>> Yeah.
>> And a guy came back and says, "Your
plane was going to fly in the
Mediterranean theater of operations.
Those go into the air intakes to stop
that sandy wind from blowing in and
clogging up your engines." And then you
can see traces of yellow paint in the
handle, so they would flag up as you're
doing your walk-around in the morning.
Right, I better take these out.
>> Yeah, you don't want to fly with them
still in, do you?
>> No, that would be a bad day.
>> And what happened to the pilot himself?
>> Yes. So, Second Lieutenant Milo Rundall
from Iowa.
He then goes to Tunisia and less than a
month later he is shot down and he ends
up being captured and then taken to
Stalag Luft III and he was there for the
rest of the war and he was there during
the time when the Great Escape was
taking place.
>> Is he still with us?
>> No, sadly passed away in 2006, but his
his daughter tells us that
he was a great patriot, loved the P-38
and he did a lot of flying after the war
as well, but a lot of time for the P-38.
And when I said, "What What do you think
he would think of what, you know, we and
the pupils are doing here?" And he said,
"Like that generation, he would have
laughed. He said, 'What are you doing,
you know, looking after my old P-38, you
know, what's all the fuss about?'" He
was just that, you know, greatest
generation type of a character.
>> Although the Second World War happened
just 80 years ago and we have plenty of
historical records of the time,
archaeology provides us with different
insights and personal connections with
this important episode in our country's
history.
>> [snorts]
>> We might be a small island, but we've
got an epic history.
And there's a wealth of untold secrets
still to uncover.
So, every year hundreds of
archaeologists dig, dive, and sift to
find clues.
>> I've never seen anything like
>> Anything like it before. It's amazing.
>> In 2018, their discoveries have been
more exciting than ever.
>> Look at that.
>> So, is that from a tank, then? That's
brilliant.
That's a nice find.
>> Not bad for day two.
>> Not bad at all.
>> Each excavation [music] has been filmed
as it happened by the archaeologists
themselves.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah, right in the middle.
>> Yeah. dig diaries mean that we can be
there for every exciting moment of
discovery.
>> Can you imagine him looking every
shoulder trying to get away from the
enemy aircraft through that?
>> I'll be in the lab where the teams will
bring in their finds from pottery and
metalwork to human remains, and we'll
take a closer look to find out what
these new digs can tell us about our
ancestors.
Look at that.
>> Be very careful.
>> I'll walk it.
>> Careful.
Oh my goodness.
While archaeologist Raksha Dave looks
into the analysis that goes on long
after a dig is finished.
Somebody stabbed her in the back of the
head. What an awful way to go.
Welcome to Digging for Britain.
In this program, I'm joining
archaeologists in the west of the
country to share their biggest
discoveries.
At Silchester, we investigate a
monumental bathhouse, revealing how the
Romans first stamped their mark on
Britain.
>> The preservation of the blocks and the
bricks is absolutely superb.
>> In Bath, construction work beneath the
magnificent medieval Abbey takes us on
an incredible journey through the city's
multi-layered hidden past.
>> This is probably late 13th or 14th
century. Quite incredible this survived.
>> And near Winchester, a team unlock the
secrets of a vast 18th-century military
camp occupied by a hoard of German
mercenaries.
>> It's gold leaf on it. It's really really
[music] shiny. It's not the sort of
thing you'd expect in a military field
kitchen.
>> No, not at all.
And at the Museum of Somerset in [music]
Taunton, I'll discover how objects here
help us tell the story of the West.
Our first dig takes us off the coast of
Portsmouth to a major underwater
investigation into an 18th century ship
that revolutionized the Royal Navy.
There are around 40,000 ships wrecked
around the British coastline, but the
chance to excavate one is incredibly
rare. It is monumentally expensive and
usually only happens when the ship is of
national importance and under threat of
destruction. Now, both are true for HMS
Invincible, and this is the largest
underwater excavation since the Mary
Rose.
For centuries, our nation's power lay in
our maritime might. But at the start of
the 18th century, Britain's Navy was in
danger of losing its edge.
Then in 1747, the Royal Navy captured
the French ship L'Invincible, a
cutting-edge, streamlined, 74-gun ship
that could literally blow anything out
of the water.
Renamed HMS Invincible, [music]
it became the flagship of the British
Navy until it ran aground on the 19th
[music] of February, 1758.
The wreck of the Invincible provides us
with an unprecedented opportunity to
discover how the 18th century Navy was
being revolutionized.
And now that shifting sands are putting
the wreck under threat, no expense is
being spared to recover as much as
possible.
A combined team from Bournemouth
University, the Maritime Archaeology
Trust, and the National Museum of the
Royal Navy is carrying out this 2
million-pound project to salvage the
remains of the wreck.
And halfway through the 3-year project,
the clock is ticking to retrieve what
evidence is left.
>> It's all about trying to recover as much
as we can, record it as quickly as we
can because during the winter we have
high energy storm events and this is
exposing vulnerable and fragile
artifacts as well [music] as the ship
structure.
>> The maritime archaeologists rely on huge
suction tubes to suck up the sand and
blow it away from the site. They're
constantly battling the threatening
tides.
But on day one, precious artifacts begin
to surface.
One of the first things to come up, a
fully intact gunpowder barrel.
>> There would have been over 300 barrels
of gunpowder on board.
That's the gunpowder and actually you
see underwater when they're moving it,
you just get clouds of black.
It is a pretty bad smell. That's the
sulfur.
>> It's a great start indicating that some
of the key armaments are still on board.
And with their expert eyes scouring the
wreck, the divers are soon rewarded with
even more gun accessories.
>> These coins here, coins were used for
supporting the breach end of the guns,
clearly labeled with the gun type. So
here we have the 9-pounder coin and next
to it the much larger 32-pounder coin.
Everything's labeled. So when you've got
the chaos of battle going on, they know
exactly where to go to
>> get the 32-pounder coin, the 9-pounder.
>> With every new discovery, the
archaeologists are revealing why
Invincible was such a formidable ship
and it wasn't just her superlative
firepower.
>> We're learning where they stored [music]
things, how they stored things. It shows
the organization, the professionalism,
the discipline.
>> As the season nears its end, the
archaeologists suddenly make their most
exciting discovery yet.
Guns.
The Invincible bristled with an amazing
74 cannons, but until now the team had
thought that many of these had been
recovered when the ship was wrecked.
>> But what's really important about this
is an unexpected find. We assumed that
all of the guns that weren't jettisoned
[music]
were recovered from the Invincible. So,
it's great that we found these.
>> These guns are a rare and important
[music] discovery, and I've invited site
directors Dan and Dave into the studio
to discuss the team's finds and what
they've learned about the ship that
revolutionized our navy.
Dan, looking at your excavation this
ship, it looks as though it's incredibly
shallow.
>> It is. The site is only in 8 to 9 m of
water.
>> And being that shallow, presumably as
soon as you see get a storm, it's hugely
at risk because the energy of the waves
will be transmitted down.
>> Exactly.
>> Then material becomes exposed. You can
see from the two blocks at the end
there, they were identical when made and
they both ended up in the water at the
same time, but one is still perfect and
that was buried within the wreck. But
once things are exposed, they're a food
source for marine life and they just
disappear.
>> And is this one of the smaller guns that
came up?
>> Yes, this is called a swivel gun. It's
an anti-personnel weapon. So, it's when
you come close to the enemy, when you're
side by side. And we found them low down
on the ship. So, they weren't in use at
the time. So, we're learning something
new that they stored these weapons and
we're only going to bring them out when
they needed them, when they were at
close quarters with the enemy. And we
weren't expecting to find these, so it
was a really nice addition to the finds.
>> And I think one of the most overwhelming
things is the smell. Is that the rope
that we can smell?
>> That is the rope. It kind of takes you
back in time.
>> Yeah.
>> This is a smell that hasn't changed
1758. This is exactly what the sailors
would have smelt. It's that tar, it's
the pitch.
>> Yeah. And it still smells 250 years
later.
>> I know, I
I really love it. It enables us as
archaeologists to really sense what it
was like on board the ship.
>> Yeah.
>> And we found out that it's actually
junk. So, it wasn't going to be used in
the rigging. It was going to be used in
the making of these objects which are
known as gun wads.
>> So, the old rope that's in the bosun of
the ship is there to be picked up
>> part and made into these wads.
>> That's it. So, it's for the process of
uh loading and firing the guns. You
would load the cannons, ramming down
your powder charge
with this. This is a rammer head.
You would then ram down one of those
wads to kind of seal the charge. You
would then ram down the shot. And to
stop that shot rolling back out the
barrel of the gun, you would have to ram
down another wad.
>> Yeah.
>> So, they're essential.
>> And what about these pieces of wood here
with marks on? What are they?
>> These are tally sticks that went with
these wads to show which size of gun
they would be used for. So, in Roman
numerals, we have 32
>> Yeah.
>> for the 32-pounder.
>> And 24.
>> And 24 for the 24-pounder. So, this
shows the organization on board.
>> And what have you got in that box?
>> Well, what I've got here is a small
timer.
>> Ah,
>> [sighs and gasps]
>> look at that.
>> It's used for calculating the speed of
the vessel.
>> David, is that glass?
>> That's glass.
>> And it's intact?
>> It's intact as it was when the ship sank
and it was found on the shelf it was
placed on
when it was last used.
>> Can I hold it?
>> You can.
But be very careful.
>> I will be careful.
>> Okay.
>> Oh my goodness.
>> And that's a 28-second timer.
Because you run a length of rope over
the stern of the vessel with knots in
every 47 ft.
>> Yeah.
>> And after 28 seconds, the number of
knots that have run through your hands
are the speed of the vessel.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> So, they had 28 seconds. That's where
That's where comes from. That's right.
>> I just cannot believe that this has
survived intact 250 years on the seabed,
and it's made of wood and glass, and
there it is, it's perfect.
I'm a really nervous about holding it,
so I'm going to hand it back to you,
Duncan.
>> back?
>> Oh my goodness. So, what we've got here
is an astonishing demonstration of the
level of organization that was going on
in the Navy by the 18th century.
>> That's it. We have the evidence for a
well-organized,
disciplined Navy, which is a complete
contrast to the previous century, where
they're a lot more dysfunctional.
There's been catastrophic disasters due
to a lack of discipline and organization
on board.
>> This ambitious dig
>> [music]
>> has revealed exactly why HMS Invincible
became the model for future cutting-edge
ship design in the British Navy, and why
in the century that [music] followed,
Britain could boast that it ruled the
waves.
We stay in the 18th century next as we
head to Barton Farm near Winchester to a
dig that gives us a rare insight into an
unusual, forgotten moment in Britain's
military past.
Archaeologists were called in to
evaluate the site before a new housing
development got started because
historical plans recorded that a vast
military encampment had stood here in
the 18th century, housing 9,000 German
soldiers.
>> These were not prisoners of war, nor an
invading force that has somehow slipped
under the historical radar.
These troops were invited here.
>> In 1756, King George II of German
descent himself, invited an army from
Hesse in Germany over to keep Britain
safe and to wage wars against its
enemies.
>> This is the first opportunity to get a
really detailed insight into what life
was like in the Hessian camp. And also,
perhaps, a clue as to what made them
such a formidable fighting force.
>> A team from Pre-Construct Archaeology is
carrying out the dig into this unique
German camp, joined by MOD archaeologist
Richard Osgood and his team of
ex-soldiers turned archaeologists.
[music]
>> This is where the Hessians were based in
1756. They were here for 10 months in
what was a pretty cold and miserable
winter.
And to get themselves shelter, they dug
down into the solid chalk. They provided
themselves with dugouts, with field
kitchens, in quite a regular pattern.
>> The team have a contemporary
[clears throat] plan of the camp.
However, they don't know how accurate it
is or what the internal structures were
really like.
But once they start digging, the
outlines of the camp are clearly visible
in the hard chalk, and it seems to be
even more massive and highly regimented
than they thought.
>> These square features are the footprints
of field kitchens, and the camp extended
for a distance of some 1 km from roughly
where we're speaking, right over in the
far distance towards the houses over
there.
>> The whole camp is far too big to dig in
its entirety, and the team are only
focusing on the field kitchens and the
dugouts affected by the housing
development. They hope that this will
tell them [music] how both were
constructed and what living conditions
might have been like, and they quickly
find their first clues.
>> Right, so it looks like we've got the
neck of the bottle.
>> Yeah.
>> Oh, cool.
>> The glass was very similar to wine
bottles.
>> As digging continues, the team finds
further [music] tantalizing clues about
life in the German soldiers' camp.
>> We are finding loads and loads of oyster
shells. [music] We've also got
clay pipes.
It's quite tempting to think of these
Hessians actually sitting around eating
oysters, which were much more
commonplace as a food substance in those
days, and smoking away.
>> The finds are painting a picture of how
the Hessian troops whiled away the hours
waiting for action. And although this is
essentially temporary accommodation, the
dugouts are well-built and would have
been surprisingly comfortable.
>> The really lovely thing about this is
this chimney, it's a remarkable feature.
You've got a series of mortared bricks
in place, and then you've got a mortared
area up here, which forms the flue of
the chimney. And this must have been a a
real godsend, absolutely critical from
having spoken to the soldiers on the
site, is keeping yourself warm in the
dugouts.
The other thing we've got in this area
is a series of stake holes cut into the
chalk.
And those represent where timber
uprights were put in place. They would
have enabled the roof structure,
probably like a tent, to go over the
top.
>> The preservation of the dugouts is
creating a remarkably clear picture.
These were solidly built, heated
structures roofed over with canvas.
Quite cozy then, but also cramped, as up
to 50 men could have been living in each
one.
As well as the dugouts, the other main
features on site are [music] a string of
field kitchens that catered for the
9,000-strong hoard of soldiers, and
they're producing some equally
interesting finds.
>> What have you got there?
>> So, this is a mid-18th century pot, red
glazed pot. And this is in the one of
the little ovens cut into the
>> Yeah, so all of these
in cook houses.
>> Super cool. What have you found?
>> Well, I've got
a little pin,
which is beautifully preserved.
And also just found a little button.
>> I mean, that'll clean up beautifully,
won't it? Still got really nice
decoration on it, but it's also got it's
gold leaf on it, isn't it? It's really
really shiny. It's not something you'd
expect in a military field kitchen.
>> No, not at all.
This is such an intriguing and unusual
site. I've invited Richard and site
director [music] Paul into the lab to
find out more.
>> I think sites like this are great. We've
got a very clear idea of what's there
from this map, but actually still it's
quite difficult to imagine how this
plays out on the ground and you know,
the organization of it. So to have this
opportunity is fantastic.
>> Yeah, to know the actual structural form
of these these dugouts and the kitchens
and the sorts of elements that they
indicate about the lives of the people
that were here in 1756. You can get a
certain amount from this, but you you've
got to do the digging to find out.
>> Cuz looking at this it just looks like a
tented camp, doesn't it? You not really
given that idea that it's
>> Yeah, it's like a kind of plastering
brick or something, isn't
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah, well it's slightly regimented last
year, isn't it?
>> Exactly. It'd be better lose.
>> And Richard, you're there digging with
soldiers who are in Operation
Nightingale. Were they impressed?
>> a real envy that they had such nice
features in the in the 1750s compared to
what they call shell scrapes nowadays
and just little gouges into the ground
where these things were beautifully
constructed with staircases and
>> fireplaces and
some some of them with ledges to sit on
perhaps and there's
>> For candles for candles in some places.
They're quite ornate in many ways and
it's
yeah, perhaps surprising when you when
you think of the the conditions of the
time that they have put so much effort
into into building these structures.
>> And that button we saw coming up in the
trench, didn't we?
>> Yeah, that's the one from the one of the
field kitchens. So it's you see the the
the shiny gilding on it.
>> Yeah, they're quite ornate for soldiers,
aren't they?
>> look military, do they? They don't look
martial. I mean we're tempted to think
that you see the the little schematic
illustrations in the one of these locals
coming out to look at the the Hessians
cuz they must have been a real curiosity
for folks
>> what these That's what these people in
the carriage are seeing.
>> And it's tempting to think that sort of
ornate button just might be dropped from
one of these people who come to see
their allies in the field in Winchester.
>> And you recovered quite a few finds
giving us a bit of an insight into the
day-to-day lives of these soldiers.
>> Yes, soldiers spend a lot of time
waiting for things to happen, don't
they? And you imagine that they they
spent a lot of time eating and smoking
and drinking day after day, month after
month.
Um and here we have a a very nice
example of an enameled um
glass uh schnapps bottle that uh
presumably one of the members of the
army actually brought with him, you
know, with his own supply of special
spirits perhaps.
>> German schnapps.
Okay. I think what's particularly
interesting
is that when you think of an efficient
army, very often we focus on, you know,
what they're doing in battle, tactics,
all of that sort of thing. But [music]
actually this is equally important, if
if actually not more important, how you
keep troops well-fed,
uh comfortable, in good fighting form
when you're not [music] actually on the
front line.
>> Yeah, without decent logistics and
morale,
um you're you're not going to succeed.
And so that that's [music] a crucial
part of the story for sure.
>> Yeah.
The dig has given us a unique insight
[music] into a forgotten moment in our
military history. The order and
sophistication of the camp revealing why
the Hessians were such crack troops and
were invited over by George II, the
Second.
And here at the museum in Somerset, a
rather personal item belonging to the
king himself provides another insight
into George's military campaigns and his
connections with Germany.
>> Tom, tell me about these trousers then.
Oh, in fact, they're not really
trousers, are they?
>> Well, I think we need to call them
breeches. That's what they would have
been called at the time. They're
remarkable because they belong to no
less a person than George II, the
Second, King of England for 33 years
from 1727 to 1760. And more remarkably,
he wore them at the Battle of Dettingen
in Germany. And it was the very last
time an English monarch led his troops
into battle.
>> Quite an extraordinary item to be
wearing and incredibly colorful. I mean,
you know, he was not going for
camouflage here.
>> No, he wanted to be a visible symbol of
monarchy and of leadership and he was
renowned as being a very brave
sovereign.
>> So, he would have cut a fine and very
noticeable figure wearing these bright
red breeches and they've got gorgeous
gold buttons as well.
>> They have, yes. The buttons are a a very
fine embellishment.
>> They're very beautiful. The the material
is slightly felty to the touch.
Beautifully fine stitching and I've
noticed that the pockets are made of
incredibly fine leather. So, I've I've
heard of kid gloves, but here are kid
pockets.
>> pockets, yes.
>> Yeah.
>> They're of the very highest quality and
as I suppose you'd expect for the for
the King of England and the Elector of
Hanover.
Um he didn't settle for second best even
when when he was on the battlefield.
>> So, was George still at this point
a ruler of Hanover?
>> Yes, he was. He throughout his life he
he had two roles as Elector of Hanover
and as
King of England.
Um
>> But these Hanoverian connections surely
explain why he later brings over the the
troops, the Hessian troops.
>> When he arrived in England in 1727, he
found an army which was under strength
and not at all experienced.
And Hessian troops were really the means
by which he strengthened the the British
army and made it fit for battle in
European campaigns.
>> So, how did the breeches end up here in
the Museum of Somerset?
>> Well, they were purchased in 1982 as
part of a job lot of costume. So, that
it's partly an accident, but it's a
happy accident because some of the
troops who fought at Dettingen were the
13th Regiment of Foot who became the
Somerset Light Infantry.
>> So, there is a Somerset connection and
Somerset men would have seen George II
riding into battle in these resplendent
breeches.
>> They would and it's very good that they
survived and rather remarkable that they
have.
>> Yeah.
Our next investigation takes us to
Salisbury and into the labs of Wessex
Archaeology where experts are analyzing
over 100 skeletons from a recently
unearthed 19th century pauper's
graveyard.
In 2016, Wessex Archaeology began
working alongside developers who were
about to build on the disused New Covent
Garden Flower [music] Market site in
Battersea, London.
150 years ago, a graveyard occupied this
site, but everyone thought that it had
been fully removed in the 1960s.
So, the team was surprised to find that
a 100-m strip at the edge of the
cemetery still remained. In the 19th
century, this was where the poorest
would have been buried. So, it's an
exciting discovery.
These skeletons have to be exhumed
[music] ready for reburial, but this
gives us a precious opportunity to look
at life and death for some of the
poorest people in 19th [music] century
Britain just as cities were becoming
utterly transformed by
industrialization.
To find out what the post-excavation
work can tell us about these
individuals, archaeologist Raksha Dave
is visiting the Wessex Labs and meeting
osteoarchaeologist Kirsty Dinwiddy.
>> I want to find out how months of
forensic work is building up a detailed
picture of the lives of each individual.
The skeleton currently being analyzed is
a middle-aged woman.
>> So, what we do
is you use this osteometric board, then
you put the bone in.
>> Okay, very gentle there.
>> Yeah.
Right, so that is 44 cm.
>> Okay, so that indicates a fairly average
stature.
>> The thing that I have noticed whilst
picking up this bone
>> Yeah.
>> is it looks really odd around here. It's
a bit lumpy bumpy.
>> It's very lumpy bumpy. If you turn it
over,
you can see it really is
>> quite disfigured.
>> Around bone, you have
a membrane called the periosteum. And if
that gets inflamed or irritated in any
way, it can cause the bone to overgrow.
So, what would have caused that?
>> Well, any kind of inflammation, so it
could be a direct trauma, but this
doesn't look like that. The other cause
could be some kind of infection
throughout the body that might irritate
and and cause this reaction. And I've
got fairly conclusive proof that she
suffered from syphilis.
If we look at the skull here,
it's quite difficult to show, but if you
look
>> Oh, I can see actually from this angle.
So, this side is kind of smooth.
>> Yeah.
>> And then there's kind of like these
knobbly bits here.
>> Yeah.
The particular lesions, they're they're
very characteristic of syphilis. So, it
it sort of eats away at the bone, but
then it starts healing. And as it heals,
it sort of folds and rolls into the
edges, so you get this kind of star-like
pattern. And if you look at this,
I can actually change the direction of
the light source. And actually, you can
pick ones up.
>> Incredible.
>> said it was smooth,
you can actually see
>> It actually isn't.
>> No. There is a lesion there.
>> Do we know if the syphilis was actually
contracted or was it congenital?
>> Um we think that it was congenital, so
that means that her mother had the
disease and passed it on to her.
>> So, she had syphilis all her life?
>> Yeah.
>> Do we know how she died?
>> Unusually so, we do in this case.
If we just take her skull here,
do you notice anything?
>> Is that what I think is? Is that a
puncture wound?
>> Yes, it is.
>> And am I right in thinking if this was
an old wound,
you would have actually seen signs of
the bone regrowing back into that?
>> That's right. And there's absolutely no
sign of that at all. And if you notice,
it's all sort of folded in.
>> Somebody stabbed her in the back of the
head.
>> Yeah, so that's just behind the right
ear.
>> What an awful way to go. This poor
woman.
>> This woman's murder may well have been
unreported as was often the case in
poorer areas.
But the prevalence of chronic diseases
was documented. Surveys suggest that
around 10% of the urban poor had
syphilis.
And further work here on a male skeleton
is proving just how tough life was in
Battersea's 19th century slums.
>> There is something that I can see.
>> Yes.
>> And it's pretty obvious.
That it looks like somebody's sawn the
top of his head off.
>> That's exactly what they've done. He's
had a cranial autopsy. [music] And if
you look
at the cut marks all around there, you
can see where the teeth of the saw have
gone round.
>> Oh yeah, cuz you can actually see the
jagged movements that they've made.
>> In the 19th century, a craniotomy,
removing the top of the head to look at
the brain, was a common form of autopsy,
especially if, like this man, the
individual had suffered psychological or
physical problems.
>> And his skull can tell us quite an
interesting story.
>> I can see immediately that the bridge of
his nose has disappeared.
>> Yes, it's been completely flattened,
probably by a number of blows to the
bridge of his nose.
>> He's obviously been in a fight.
>> I think he's been in more than one
fight. He's been in several fights. If
you think it's a classic boxer's nose,
so it's almost straight like that. And
also, he has actually lost his front
teeth.
>> Do you think that's related to his his
fighting injuries?
>> It could well be. And there's a canal
that joins [music]
the nasal area to the mouth, and
sometimes if that gets damaged, it can
form a cyst in the the area of trauma.
And if you can see the shadow
of a cyst, then um it's got so large
that actually
it's worn away the bones there.
>> Gosh, that must have been
incredibly painful.
>> Yeah, I mean the pressure must have been
quite uncomfortable. You could have had
surgery to remove that, but he certainly
wouldn't have had the money. So, he
would have had to have put up with that
for his life.
>> Just from these two skeletons, it's
clear that for many the streets of early
industrialized London certainly weren't
paved with gold. Disease was rife, and
looking at these individuals, beaten,
bruised, and murdered, life was pretty
brutal.
Our next dig takes us to Silchester in
Hampshire.
Originally an Iron Age settlement, it
grew into a Roman town, and since its
discovery in 1864, it's been one of the
richest Roman sites in Britain, offering
a whole range of clues about the life of
our Romano-British ancestors.
Silchester is an exciting and important
Roman site because the town Calleva
Atrebatum fell into disuse rapidly and
was never built over. So, what we have
is a perfectly preserved Roman town.
University of Reading archaeologists
have been digging there for more than 20
years, and this year they returned to
focus on one particular area, the
bathhouse. Now, this important public
building should yield clues about how
the Romans stamped [music] their
identity on Britain.
>> We've chosen the baths, one of the
principal public buildings of the town,
because there are questions about when
the baths were built, how long they
lasted, and about life in the baths.
What sort of activities took place? The
eating, the gambling, the half [__]
the massage, you know, all that sort of
activity. What can we trace from the
soil itself and from the artifacts that
we find?
>> Because the bathhouse was originally
[music] dug 100 years ago, Mike knows
exactly where it's located.
And since Silchester was never built on
after the Romans left,
>> [music]
>> its foundations are quickly revealed and
it's not long until the team start
uncovering [music] the precious Roman
artifacts they've been hoping for.
>> Can we see the coin, Libby?
That's really clear, isn't it?
>> Yes, you've [music] got a little figure
and maybe a spear or flagpole or
something.
>> Yeah.
>> Perhaps a torch in the other hand.
>> There is a head on the other side but
you can't see it very clearly. It
doesn't have a beard which makes it
quite early and pre-Hadrian.
>> The discovery of such an early coin is
promising. It suggests that the
bathhouse must have been built by at
least the early 2nd century.
But what's really exciting is the
discovery of personal items inside the
bathhouse.
>> I have got a stylus.
They would be used as writing implements
for wax tablets and when you hold it in
your hands, you can feel how they
balanced it which is really nice.
>> Not bad for day two.
>> Not bad at all.
>> The Roman lost property provides an
intriguing insight into what was going
on in the bathhouse and into who was
visiting it 2,000 years ago. They're
finding a quantity of rings, necklaces
and hairpins suggesting that many of the
bathers were women.
>> So here we have these bone weaving
tablets that would have been used to
separate the threads while they were
weaving. Almost complete. So whether
this is specifically a ladies area if
we're finding the jewelry, the hairpins,
the weaving tablets, a rather lovely
lovely find.
>> As the archaeologists delve deeper,
they're beginning to reveal astonishing
details of the form and fabric of the
bathhouse itself.
>> The quality of the masonry, the
preservation of the blocks and the
bricks is absolutely superb. I mean,
nowhere else, not even within
Silchester, will you get preservation of
this quality.
>> And as the dig reaches its third week,
the team hit the water table with
astonishing results.
Water begins to flow through the drains
just as it would have done 2,000 years
ago.
With the foundations in such great
condition, the team now hopes that
they'll be able to answer the real
question at the heart of their mission.
When was [music] the bathhouse built?
Frustratingly, this key fact has eluded
them so far. But on the last day, the
archaeologists finally find the evidence
they need.
>> It looks like we found what we were
hoping for from this excavation, and
that is a [music] Nero stamped tile.
When we use these tracings from existing
tiles that we have,
the circle fits exactly with the inner
and the outer circles. [music] So, it's
exactly the right dimensions to be a
Nero tile.
>> The stamp dates the tiles securely to
the time of the Emperor Nero's reign.
And this is much earlier than expected.
I've invited dig director Mike into the
[music] lab to discuss the significance
of this surprise.
>> Mike, you've re-excavated [music] this
bathhouse, but what you've done is find
this really important bit of dating
evidence that you've actually got a Nero
tile associated with the bathhouse for
the first time.
>> Yes, that's right. And this is the only
place in Britain where we have these
tiles.
>> So, with Nero's name, what what date
does that give us?
>> Well, it must be sometime after 54. Nero
became emperor in 54. The initial
invasion began in 43.
So, sometime, you know, within the first
20 years, they're building the baths.
And this is one of the earliest mortared
masonry architecturally designed
buildings in Roman Britain that
survives.
>> So, this is taking in what was an Iron
Age settlement and totally transforming
it. You know, this is now very
[clears throat] much a Roman town on
Roman plans.
>> This is yes, stamping your if you like
your symbol of Roman civilization,
putting a bathhouse on what was a major
Iron Age center, which you can no longer
see through prism of the Roman town
plan.
>> So, how does this work as a building
then? You come in here, what are the
various rooms?
>> So, peristyle, so that's your walk,
exercise, warm up, then you come in,
this is the changing space, and then you
run through the different range of rooms
going through warm, tepidarium,
to hot, the caldarium.
>> Mhm. So, this caldarium, this is where
you've got the hypocaust underneath, so
heated floors.
>> Heated floors, hot room, the furnace is
outside.
>> So, sauna effectively.
>> Yes, yes. And then you round it off with
the cold plunge back here.
>> And plenty of women, it seems, coming
and using these baths.
>> Yes, men at the moment largely
invisible,
but yes, we've got a range of finger
rings, of which a piece de resistance is
this
gold finger ring.
>> Oh, isn't that lovely? Quite tiny.
>> Yes, that's for a a lady or even
conceivably for a child.
>> Yeah.
>> And this is another lovely one here, but
a different material. Um, this is
glass.
>> Oh, it's just beautiful. So, these are
little items, you know, personal
jewelry, which people have lost at the
baths.
>> Yes, yes.
Um, but what they lose in abundance are
these hairpins. Um,
>> Yeah. So, it's just the same today,
isn't it? It's the hairbands. No, I
think it's the women who are always
losing hairbands and their hairbands.
And these are bone, are they?
>> They're bone, yes.
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> And
>> That's lovely. And do we know who was
living there? I mean, is this going to
be Roman citizens coming in from the
empire or is this is this Brits?
>> I think predominantly it's it's Brits.
Um,
I mean, the town is one of the biggest
centers in Britain at the time of the
Roman conquest, and a natural center
perhaps to develop.
>> I mean, it is just extraordinary, isn't
it? Yeah, arriving in a new place and
going like, "Look how lucky you are.
We've We've built you a bath here."
>> Yes, and it's a remarkable story that
early investment in Roman Britain, the
confidence of Rome in its newly found
province.
>> Early and rapid investment.
>> Early and rapid investment, yes.
>> Discovering this early date for
Silchester's bath house is fantastic.
It's fresh evidence about the
determination and speed with which the
Roman Imperial machine stamped their
mark on Britain after the conquest.
When the Romans arrive in Britain, they
bring a new culture with them including
characteristic styles of architecture
and clothing, pottery and glassware, and
of course a new language. But there are
other less tangible aspects of Roman
culture that also arrived, ideas,
stories and myths, and these are
beautifully encapsulated in a fantastic
artifact here in the museum.
A lot, this is such a gorgeous museum.
How was it discovered?
>> Well, we didn't know anything about it
until 1938 when Herbert Cook, a local
farmer, found a sheep dead in his field.
>> Right.
>> Um and he set about burying it and in
that hole he found a little fragment of
a clay tile. So, he decided to take it
to the museum to get it identified. Um
it wasn't until 1945 that a schoolboy
read about the tile, went to see Herbert
Cook, and the two of them dug another
hole just by chance immediately above
the mosaic.
>> Fantastic. So, if it wasn't for the dead
sheep and the schoolboy, we wouldn't
have this.
>> We wouldn't know.
>> I mean, it's so beautifully preserved,
isn't it? And then obviously it got
lifted at some point.
>> Yeah, in 1953, it was quite a big
operation to move it. So, they stuck
fabric to it and rolled it up a bit like
a carpet.
>> doing here, they're they're just rolling
it up and you can see the pieces of
tesserae there. I mean, it's a gorgeous,
gorgeous mosaic and I love the fact that
it tells a story.
>> Yes, and in fact it's the oldest objects
in Britain which tells a complete story.
>> Is it? Oh, that's fantastic.
>> The mosaic illustrates a chapter from
one of the greatest Roman myths written
down by the Roman poet Virgil in the 30s
BCE.
This part focuses on the tragic love
story of the legendary hero Aeneas and
the Carthaginian Queen Dido.
>> So, it starts here. Aeneas is [music] a
refugee from his hometown in Troy, which
is in modern-day
>> Turkey.
>> Yeah.
>> And he's crossing the Mediterranean on
his way to Italy where it's his destiny
to found the city of Rome. And uh his
ships get wrecked on the coast of North
Africa.
>> Right.
>> So, it then moves to this central panel
at the back.
>> Yeah.
>> Um and that shows Aeneas leaning
nonchalantly on his spear.
>> Yeah.
>> And then
>> And that's Is that Dido then?
>> That's Dido, yeah.
And next to Aeneas is Cupid because
Venus, who's the third figure along,
who's the goddess of love and also
Aeneas's mother, has decided that she
wants to make Aeneas and Dido fall in
love.
>> Okay.
>> So, she's sent Cupid in to make that
happen.
>> And is it working?
>> I think it is, yeah. He's kind of
plucking at her shawl, which in
classical art is a sort of flirtatious
gesture, so
>> Is it?
>> it seems like Cupid's already working
his magic. So, then we it moves on to
the panel on which shows a hunting
scene. Got Dido at the back, Aeneas in
the middle.
>> Not wearing any clothes.
>> No, he's got boots on.
>> [laughter]
>> And uh big storm happens. So, Dido and
Aeneas seek shelter in a cave.
>> Oh, right.
>> This panel here.
>> Oh, so the denouement of the story. They
seem to be falling in love with each
other.
>> They do, yes. They're embracing and they
spend the night together in the cave.
>> So, what does happen at the end of the
story then? Dido commits suicide.
>> She does, yeah. Aeneas decides to leave
to get on with his mission to found Rome
and set sail without telling Dido. Uh
Dido is absolutely distraught
and decides that the only option is to
kill herself.
>> It's such a tragic story.
>> yeah.
>> Um, but it's fantastic to have this
story so beautifully laid out. And you
can imagine people in that villa walking
around telling the story as you've just
done.
>> Definitely. I think it's about the
person who commissioned the mosaic
showing off his Roman heritage.
>> Yeah.
>> And weaving this Roman story into the
decoration of his house.
>> Definitely, yeah.
>> Our next dig is taking place in the
historic city of Bath, where Wessex
Archaeology have been given an
incredible opportunity.
They're digging right in the center,
beneath Bath Abbey, one of Britain's
most beautiful historic monuments
brimming with an immensely rich and
ancient past.
>> The current Abbey at Bath was largely
built in the 16th century on the site of
an earlier Norman Cathedral, and then it
was extensively renovated in the 19th
century.
But now its structure is under threat.
The Victorian heating system desperately
needs updating, and the floor is
starting to collapse. Well, now there's
a 19 million pound restoration project
underway, and that's giving
archaeologists a golden opportunity to
investigate what lies beneath the floor
of the Abbey.
The lucky team from Wessex Archaeology
have 2 years to unlock the Abbey's
secrets.
>> Welcome to day one of our dig diary.
We're getting our tools together,
getting the structures in place for us
to be able to go down into the vaults.
>> Before the construction work happens,
the archaeologists have to evaluate
every inch of the site, and it's not an
easy task.
>> Um, this is quite a good example of how
tricky some of the excavation is. We
have to work around lots of live
services. It's all very cramped in
places.
>> The vaults lie 3.5 m beneath street
level [music] and all crisscrossed with
water pipes and cables.
And the archaeologists seem to discover
medieval remains amongst these modern
services, proof that the site is going
to be highly complicated.
>> This man would have been [music]
absolutely huge, especially for medieval
standards. So, it's yeah, quite
>> What sort of height are we looking at?
>> I'm looking at yeah, about 6 ft 5.
>> 6 ft 5?
>> Yeah, about twice the size of me.
>> As well as a medieval burial, the vaults
also reveal evidence of Bath's ancient
Roman origins.
>> And what we've got is demolished a Roman
hypocaust,
which is basically an underfloor heating
system. And here we've got lots of
tesserae, which would have been the
mosaic floor that covered the top of it.
>> The team is getting plenty of glimpses
of Bath's rich historic past underneath
the pipes, and they're coming across
some unexpected surprises, too.
>> So, we've got a really nice curving wall
around here.
It goes under the foundations here, so
it's definitely pretty early.
Also, it looks like there might be some
wall facing on it, so we think they're
probably upstanding walls
and potentially earlier than medieval
because there were the cloisters here,
and this should have really been an open
space, but
there's been wall [snorts] here, so
>> Who knows?
>> This complicated site is throwing up as
many questions [music] as answers.
And as the team starts work on the floor
of the Abbey itself, it soon becomes
clear why it needs [music] replacing.
>> This is a grave. There's a coffin
underneath that's collapsed, and it's
left a hole above it where all the
soil's collapsed down into the coffin.
>> There are an estimated 9,000 burials
beneath the Abbey, and insufficient
underpinning explains why the Victorian
floor is now collapsing.
But 2 m deeper down, the archaeologists
make a completely unexpected discovery.
>> Lovely, isn't it? It's uh Tudor and
green tiles.
We've got an intact medieval floor
surface here, uh decorated with these
tiles. We believe this is probably late
13th or 14th century. We've got various
designs. Over here, we've got the uh
three lions on a shield, which is the uh
the arms of the Plantagenet kings.
Over here, we have the arms of the de
Clare family, which are powerful Marcher
lords of Caerphilly Castle. Quite
incredible this has survived.
>> This is a wonderful end to the first
year of the Bath Abbey Footprint
Project. So, I've asked Cai into the
studio to discuss these findings.
Oh, Cai, this is absolutely incredible.
You're finding so much. You've got a
real kind of microcosm of the whole
history of Bath, haven't you? You're
getting you right back to the Roman
layers, and then coming through to the
Norman and medieval layers.
>> It goes right through, and so it's
really got a little bit of everything.
>> Yeah. I mean, I think the really curious
thing was this curved wall. So, do you
know what that is now?
>> Possibly. So, app structures, curved
walls tend to occur in two places.
Either you get them in Roman buildings,
um and you get them at the east end of
churches or chapels.
>> Yeah.
>> So, we're right next door to the baths,
and you can see here there's a whole
series of similar-looking structures.
So, we thought, could it be part of
that? But the mortar's different. It's
much more similar to the medieval
structures.
>> Mhm.
>> So, the next thing we thought is, could
it be part of the Norman Cathedral?
The problem is,
>> that's where it is.
>> It's here. It's right in the middle of
the cloisters, and you shouldn't have
any buildings in this position. That
this should be open space.
>> So, this uh in blue on the plan, that's
the footprint of the Norman building,
and these are the cloisters.
And there's your apps.
>> That's right, yeah. So, the other
possibility is that it could be part of
an earlier church, a late Saxon church.
>> Oh, really?
>> Um now, we also have a number of Saxon
burials in this area, so it could be. We
just don't have quite enough to prove it
at the moment.
>> How curious. So, there's a phase of
demolition in the 16th century when the
new Abbey is built, and then more
demolition and disturbance in the
Victorian period.
>> Yeah, so the east end of the Tudor Abbey
had a a fan vaulted stone ceiling, but
the nave itself, they built a wooden
ceiling there with plaster decoration on
it. Um which we've found evidence of.
>> And this is some of it, is it?
>> Yeah, so when the the Victorian
restoration happened, they essentially
ripped out what they saw as things that
didn't match the original design, which
included this, and we we found um dozens
and dozens of these little um rosettes
amongst other decorative plaster. So, it
gives us a really good idea of what the
um the ceiling of the Abbey looked like.
>> So, this is Tudor.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah.
And what about that tile?
>> So, this tile, I believe this is early
15th century, and uh this coat of arms
is the coat of arms of King Edmund, the
the first King of England, who was um
incidentally crowned at Bath Abbey. He
wouldn't have recognized his arms cuz it
was invented about 300 years after he
died, um but the kings of the time um
thought that he was a king, therefore he
needed a coat of arms. So, this is what
they created.
>> that's amazing to find these tiles. What
about this coin?
What's that?
>> Yeah, so this was uh a bit of a
surprise. Um this was um actually found
by the workmen when they were lifting
the pews inside the Abbey.
>> It's got a little devil on it. It says
the city of the devil, civitas diaboli.
>> Yeah, and on the other side it's got a
date, um and uh the name Anholt, which
is an island off the coast of Denmark.
>> It's a recent date, 1973.
That's actually the same vintage as me.
>> [laughter]
>> So, we looked into this a little bit,
and the the date it describes is when 13
supposedly ritual sites were found on
this island. And one of them had a fake
shrunken head on it. And people started
to think this is some kind of cult
activity. And shortly after this, these
coins started appearing in churches all
over Denmark and Sweden. Nobody knew
where they were coming from. And then in
2013, it turned out it was all the work
of a clerk at the Danish National
Gallery. And it was all an elaborate
hoax.
>> Really?
>> Yeah.
>> Isn't that amazing? A little devil under
the floor in Bath Abbey site.
Although just halfway through, this dig
is already providing rare glimpses of
what lies beneath one of our most
treasured historic cities. And with a
year to go, who knows what other secrets
will be uncovered.
Next, it's back to Wessex Archaeology in
Salisbury, where Raksha is with
archaeologists who are investigating the
remains of an early 19th century
pauper's graveyard.
And it's becoming clear just how
terrible the living conditions were at
the time.
>> Rachel, you were the site director for
this excavation.
>> How was the preservation on site?
>> on site was really very good. We found
organic remains that we wouldn't expect
to find.
>> So, what have you got in that dish over
there? Cuz that looks rather curious.
>> It is. And it's not something that
[music] you would expect to find very
often. This is a desiccated brain.
>> That's rather small. Is that just a
portion of the brain?
>> No, this is a complete brain. But this
is a brain from a 9- or 10-year-old
child.
>> And is that from this individual?
>> Yes, it is. We did find quite a large
number of children. And this is one of
the children that we found.
>> I can see here that there's green
staining around the eyes.
>> Yes, so this is where coins were placed
over the child's eyes. The parents,
although they were very likely to have
been incredibly poor, cared an awful lot
for their children. And one of the ways
they've shown that is by placing the
coins on the eyes. Coins they could
probably very ill afford.
>> And you have another child skeleton
here.
>> Yes, we do. And this was probably the
most poignant find we had from the
entire site. This was an individual that
still had a legible nameplate as we
uncovered it. So, we could decipher part
of the legible nameplate. We could
decipher the date she died and how old
the nameplate said she was. Next to you,
you'll see a photograph.
And
this was her nameplate. She was called
Jane Clara Joy and she died at age 1
year. We've been able to find her
baptism certificates and her death
certificates.
>> Do we know very much about her?
>> We know a little bit. We know that she
was 22 months when she passed away. Um
her father was a laborer called George.
And she lived in the Nine Elms area of
Battersea.
>> And by studying her skeleton, can you
tell how she died?
>> The bones tell us that it was probably
some sort of chronic or severe infection
that killed her.
>> So, is infant mortality high?
>> Infant mortality is extremely high. Um
in the streets surrounding this site,
the infant mortality is 25% on average
for this period. There's an awful lot of
industrialization within the Battersea
area. So, you're getting [music]
chemical factories, acid factories, some
really nasty stuff. And it's quite grim
living conditions for these people.
>> So, this is very commonplace. It's
literally survival of the fittest.
>> It's survival of the fittest and the
luckiest. Um there were a lot of
diseases like cholera, typhoid. If you
were fortunate enough, you might make it
to adulthood. And if [music] you were
unfortunate or unwell, you would end up
as poor Jane Clara Joy did within the
cemetery.
>> Our final dig takes us to the ancient
monument of Barrow Clump on Salisbury
Plain in Wiltshire, where archaeologists
are investigating a cache of richly
furnished burials.
Barrow Clump is a 3,000-year-old Bronze
Age burial mound, a barrow lying just 5
miles west of Stonehenge.
It's such a big feature in the [music]
landscape that 1,500 years later, the
Anglo-Saxons chose to bury their dead
here, too.
But now, this site is potentially in
danger of destruction.
>> Archaeological sites can be threatened
by anything from the construction of new
roads and railways to coastal erosion.
But at our next site, Barrow Clump, the
problem was a little more unusual.
>> Salisbury Plain is an MOD training
ground, and military vehicles
continually thunder by during maneuvers.
To assess whether this has caused any
damage, a familiar face, MOD
archaeologist Richard Osgood, is
investigating with his team of
ex-soldiers.
>> Morning one on Barrow Clump, summer
2018. Stripping an area underneath the
track to see the effects of ground
pressure of vehicles on the Prehistoric
cemetery that lies below.
>> Only digging will reveal the true extent
of this cemetery, that is, if the
precious evidence hasn't been destroyed
by the tanks.
But the initial signs are promising.
>> Morning three on Barrow Clump, and the
graves are emerging. There's an area of
burning, which has got human bone on top
of it, and next to that, there's another
complete grave.
>> But as they dig down, the team's
confidence about the level of
preservation is shaken.
>> Here's skull.
>> Yeah.
Believe this could be the shoulder,
um
pelvis,
and then legs.
>> Okay, so it's looking at
looking a bit friable. The bones look a
bit delicate, is that right, at the
moment?
>> Skulls, as you can see.
>> Yeah, it's skull, isn't it?
>> Yeah. Part of the skull there, so it's
actually broken.
>> Okay.
>> The level of survival is disappointing,
and for the next few days things don't
improve but on day four
>> We have a square headed brooch here
which probably comes in a pair
and further down the trench there's a
little bit of green coming out there.
>> Brooches like this are often found in
graves of wealthy Anglo-Saxon women.
The discovery is a welcome sign that
further valuable evidence might survive.
And as other burials are uncovered the
team finds grave goods often associated
with male burials.
>> We found the grave cut that goes all the
way around towards a really nice [music]
shield boss.
>> That is really good nick isn't it?
>> It's lovely. Yeah, it's really nice.
>> The boss is the metal centerpiece to a
wooden shield that is entirely rusted
away.
Anglo-Saxon men were often buried with
shields laid over them.
And there are more metal artifacts
clearly hidden beneath the ground.
>> Getting a stronger iron signal dead
center of the small pit there so
slowly go down.
>> Every bleep of the metal detector
increases the anticipation on site.
And on the final day the team uncovers
what for them is the most exciting find
of the entire dig.
>> What you got? Can't have a
sword?
>> That's really cool. You can see the
hilt.
>> And the bones are still on the remains.
>> And after hours of careful excavation
the incredible preservation of this rare
object is apparent.
>> Wow.
Wow.
>> So that's the end of the year at Barrow
Clump. We've had 27 graves and probably
the most spectacular being the
individual buried in the grave in front
of me with his sword and all the grave
fittings. A really, really astonishing
sight. But this must be the most
spectacular we've had so far.
>> I've invited Richard into the studio
with that sword to discuss all of the
finds from Barrow Clump this year.
>> It's quite incredible to think that this
man, he's right underneath the tank
tracks.
>> That's right. We were looking this year
just to see how damaging our military
vehicles were. And the answer is
actually it's not doing a huge amount of
damage. And yes, this was quite a
spectacular find in the last week of the
dig.
>> You seem quite excited to find the sword
at the end.
>> If you're digging with a military team,
they all want to find weaponry. And what
could be more perfect than something as
wonderful as this, really?
>> Yeah.
>> It's in pretty good condition. It has
the scabbard mouth there made of bronze,
possibly a horn handle to it. And then
to find this with what the the soldiers
perceived as a warrior.
>> Yeah.
>> Um it is quite something. He had a
spear, he had um a ring-headed pin, and
gloriously had tweezers as well.
>> So these are tweezers?
>> Yeah, some iron tweezers. And we found
little bronze tweezers with female
burials before, but it it it was good to
see that he too had a a part of a toilet
set with him, a part of his his his
grooming.
>> Yeah, he would have looked after
himself.
>> Yeah, absolutely so.
>> And of course, just because you found
weaponry, a magnificent sword and a
spear, you can't assume that this is a
male burial.
But I think this time, I mean, it's very
obvious, isn't it? These are very long
bones, large joints. Looking at the jaw,
that's an incredibly robust jawline
>> very masculine then.
>> Yeah.
>> In this case, they do seem to be quite
gender specific on our site. And the the
the burials with with jewelry are of
females and the weaponry are of males.
So uh that's what we've got at Barrow
Clump.
>> So you have got quite a few female
burials. And and these are some of the
beads from from those there.
>> Yes, these are just one collection of
grave goods from a female burial, but
>> From one burial?
>> From one burial. Yes, they all come
They're absolutely stunning, aren't
they, with the the iridescent blues and
the the the orange ambers and the glass,
really really exquisite items.
>> Really lovely.
>> Um and you've got soldiers arguing who's
got the prettier jewels in the grave
they're digging. It's not something
they'd probably have expected in the
mess 10 years before. And and really
excitingly with this one was this little
brooch because this is a one-off from a
grave in Britain. This is Visigothic.
>> The Visigoths, a group that's moved from
Germany to northern Spain or southern
France and it gives us all those sort of
questions as to whether the individual
was accompanied
>> with these things, whether she was in
fact from that region or whether she's a
British woman that's adopted fashions of
another grouping.
>> I think identity is really difficult in
this period, well, any period actually,
because she might have had some Visigoth
ancestry
whilst growing up in this country. We
>> Completely that and we've had we've had
Roman brooches as well. So, that also
asks the questions whether these are
heirlooms or whether they've just been
found on Salisbury Plain, which is
always a possibility given the amount of
archaeology there.
>> Yeah. And do we know where these people
lived? And is there is there a
settlement
>> They have I.
>> Good good Saxon place names of Abington
and Fyfield, which is just just below it
on the River Avon, both mentioned in the
Domesday Book.
Um I I think that probably is where
they're they're living just down the
hill.
>> And and then presumably choosing to site
the cemetery further up the hill where
there are Bronze Age burials up there.
>> it's that continuity of landscape, isn't
it? People are are using that landscape
as a venerated spot. They're looking up
onto the hillside and I do think that
these places were significant in the
Saxon period with the knowledge that
they were where ancestors, for want of a
better word, were were placed in
prehistory.
>> Each and every dig reveals how
archaeology can shed new light on the
story of Britain.
From discovering why HMS Invincible
transformed British sea power in the
18th century
to revealing the horrific realities of
life and death for London's poor 150
years ago.
Our ancestors made the country we live
in today and through archaeology we've
been able to reach back through the
centuries and touch their lives.
We might be a small island, but we've
got an epic history.
And there's a wealth of untold secrets
still to uncover.
So every year hundreds of archaeologists
dig, dive, and sift to find clues.
>> Absolutely. Never seen anything like
>> Anything like it before. It's amazing.
>> In 2018 their discoveries have been more
exciting than ever.
>> Look at that.
So is that from a tank then?
>> It's brilliant.
>> That's a nice find.
>> Not bad for day two.
>> Not bad at all.
>> Each excavation [music]
has been filmed as it happened by the
archaeologists themselves.
Their dig diaries mean that we can be
there for every exciting [music]
moment of discovery.
>> Can you imagine him looking over his
shoulder trying to get away from the
enemy aircraft through that?
>> I'll be in the lab [music] where the
teams will bring in their finds from
pottery and metalwork to human remains
and we'll take [music] a closer look to
find out what these new digs can tell us
about our ancestors.
Look at that.
>> Be very careful.
>> I will be careful. Oh my goodness.
While archaeologist [music] Ratcher Dave
looks into the analysis that goes on
long after a dig is finished.
Somebody stabbed her in the back of the
head. What an awful way to go.
Welcome to Digging for Britain.
>> In this program, I'm joining
archaeologists in the east of Britain
and beyond as they share their biggest
discoveries. We join a team as they find
an incredible lost Stone Age monument.
>> It has to mean something and it's now
our job is to figure out what it does
mean.
>> And we uncover an unusual Roman burial
site that seems to defy explanation.
>> This is actually the 17th out of 32
which show deviancy in the form of
decapitation.
>> And at Norwich Castle Museum, I'll
discover how one of the objects held
here helps us to tell the story of
Eastern Britain. [music]
First, we travel a bit further east than
usual to investigate the key World War I
battle of Bullecourt in a French foreign
field that is forever England.
By 1917, a devastating land war had been
raging in Europe for 3 years.
That spring, Germany made the strategic
decision to retreat behind a massive
fortified defense they'd constructed
across northern France.
It was known to the British as the
Hindenburg Line.
The line was almost impenetrable with a
set of six trenches and in front of that
another 90 m of barbed wire.
The allies had to breach it though or
face the terrible prospect of an even
longer war.
So, the British decided to try out their
latest barely tested invention, the
tank.
The plan at Bullecourt was
straightforward. 12 British tanks would
advance to the Hindenburg Line, crashed
through the defenses, followed by troops
of Australian infantry.
But in the end, it was a disaster. Only
two tanks got anywhere near the line,
leading to a catastrophic loss of
Australian life.
The Australians felt badly betrayed, and
one general even accused the tank crews
of cowardice.
MOD archaeologist Richard Osgood is
leading this battlefield dig.
>> What we're looking for is the points
where the tanks of the British Army
attacked in 1917, and to find out why
they were destroyed where they were. To
answer the question that was leveled at
some of the crews that they perhaps
lacked moral fiber. Maybe there's an
element of cowardice in some ways not
helping to assist the Australian
infantry in their attack on the German
Hindenburg Line.
>> The team have an idea where they might
find one of these tanks, because the
Germans took photographs of it after
their victory.
Richard's archaeologists are ex-soldiers
from Britain, Australia, and Germany.
>> Well, the edge of the trench is about
here.
So, it has a
little slope in it.
>> They've served in recent conflicts from
Afghanistan to Iraq,
giving them an insight into war's worst
realities.
And it doesn't take long before they
find evidence of the Hindenburg Line's
brutal design.
>> What we've picked up here,
German barbed wire. You see, it's really
thick. It's well over-engineered. Pretty
nasty stuff. You'll certainly get
tangled up in that and and be shot, no
doubt.
>> And then, Richard's team are brought
face-to-face with the tragic
consequences of this battle for
Bullecourt.
A reminder that there were casualties on
both sides.
>> This chap here is a German casualty
lying in the Hindenburg Line. This is
his skull.
He's facing this way. He seems to be in
in quite a mess, doesn't he? His pelvis
is kind of twisted this way. The
vertebrae suddenly stop
there.
>> They can tell from the equipment around
him that he was a German soldier.
It's important to these former soldiers
to take a moment to remember the fallen.
>> War is a is a great leveler.
He's a human being. Could be British,
could be Australian, you could be
French. In [music] this case, he's he's
German. And it's all exactly the same.
>> Ja, um Kamerad.
Kamerad.
This is not easy, but a 100 years ago,
we might have fought against each other,
but because of this war, we're now
standing here together.
Not as enemies, but as friends.
Auf dich, Kamerad.
>> We remember fallen comrades.
>> Remember fallen comrades.
>> Fallen comrades.
>> The next day, the team continue their
quest for the tank.
>> I can't believe they're making so many
finds already. We've got lots of tank
parts that are coming out of the ground.
We've got parts of the engine, we've got
parts of the driving chain, we've got
some of the components from within the
tank as well.
>> Because of the documentary evidence and
photos, Richard knows that he's looking
at the remains of tank 796
commanded by Lieutenant Hugh Skinner.
And the only tank that made it all the
way to the Hindenburg Line, it broke
down in a crater in full view of the
German artillery.
In the reports of the battle written by
Australian generals, British tank crews
were accused of cowardice and
incompetence. So, is it possible that
Skinner and his crew abandoned their
Australian allies?
>> Got some tank
armor.
>> All right, that's part of the the plate
from the side, is it?
>> Yes, it is.
>> Being in an armored vehicle with
something like this, I mean, is that
going to protect you against shell
blast?
>> No, not at all. Protects you against
small arms.
>> So, against bullets, good. Against
shells, that's really not going to work.
So, that's pretty terrifying, isn't it?
>> Yeah.
>> The armor plating was clearly [music]
not able to withstand the firepower it
faced.
With his tank immobilized and under
heavy fire, Skinner and his crew would
have been sitting [music] ducks. So, the
last find of the dig is a revelation.
>> Leave it, leave it there, Paul.
>> And um that's possibly the end of a
shell. It is hollow.
>> Okay, we'll keep cleaning it. That that
looks a cartridge.
>> I I think so.
>> Cartridge.
>> It's got curvature.
>> So, in which case, we need to get Dave
over to have a look.
>> Was it a six-pounder case?
>> Well, that's what the guys have been
thinking.
>> Yeah, that's what it is, six-pounder
case.
>> So, so that's from a tank, then.
>> Yeah, yeah, yeah.
>> That's brilliant. That's a nice find.
>> This empty casing suggests a six-pound
tank shell was fired on this very spot.
They were firing the remains of their
ammo until the bitter end.
>> When the tank was basically broken down
here, in his report, he said he carried
on firing trying to use as much of his
ammunition up as possible before they
retreated to the Australian and British
lines over there. And this kind of
proves that he was firing from this spot
where the tank was broken.
So, this item is, yeah, it's a it's a
symbol of bravery.
>> I've asked Richard to join me in the lab
to share the powerful evidence he's
uncovered to contradict the Australian
accusations of cowardice.
>> This is basically the archeology of a
day. This is the archeology of one day
in April 1917 and the traces it leaves
behind in these in these French fields.
>> Have you found out anything else that we
couldn't have known just from the the
history that's come down to us?
>> Um yes, I mean the the armor that's just
metal is not armored as we'd understand
it. It's that sort of level of
thickness. It's really
great for stopping bullets but not for
stopping artillery. The crews must have
known that very very quickly and it must
have been just terrifying. So these are
the tanks that are brought in for
training for the British Army. They've
used them on the Somme in 1916 but this
is going to be the the breakthrough
weapon but they're only for training.
>> Mhm.
>> I suppose shock and awe is the thing
they were trying to achieve of having
this monster attacking the infantry and
that's great if you can't shoot through
it.
>> I mean it seems extraordinary that
you're saying that essentially this is a
this is a training tank. I mean this
tank is firing shells of that size and
presumably the Germans are firing back
similar size shells.
>> This is a six-pounder case and the
Germans were firing back 7.7 cm
artillery which is pretty much the same
sort of size and it was going straight
through the metal of these tanks.
>> And what's this image here?
>> We all think we know what colors the
tanks are and the only way you can
really tell what the original paint was
like on these things is if you find it
in the ground. And we were incredibly
fortunate
to find that paint of 796. So you've got
two colors there.
You've got the red which is the
undercoat
>> Mhm.
>> and then a green tone on top of it. That
color is British racing green.
>> Yeah.
>> On a thing that does 4 mph, bright green
color.
>> out more do you think?
>> done all sorts of different color
schemes and they're experimenting as
such a new weapon. They're even
experimenting with the colors that are
going on to this thing. People are
learning lessons and desperately trying
to break through this huge siege that's
going on on on the Western Front.
>> So, the Germans had nothing like this?
>> No, nothing at all. In fact, the the
main use of tanks the Germans have in
the First World War captured British
tanks, Beutepanzer. Um
it's a bit of a Pyrrhic victory in some
ways in that the Germans look at the
results of the fire that they put out
against these tanks and where they've
destroyed them and how they've destroyed
them, and they employ those tactics
later on in other battles. But, by then
the British are not using training
tanks, they're using properly armored
vehicles.
>> Right.
>> And that leads to successes like the
Battle of Cambrai just a few months
later where there are much more
effective vehicles.
>> And what about this this tale of Cardiff
then? I mean, where does this excavation
leave us?
>> Well, well, hopefully that's
dispelled any sorts of thoughts like
that. It comes from the Australians who
took a lot of casualties in this one
particular battle, perhaps looking for a
scapegoat, and these tank crews were
that obvious example to to pin it on.
The fact this tank got as far as it did,
it fired until its ammunition was either
expended or the tank was utterly unable
to maintain itself without being
destroyed. It does 4 mph over a big
area. They've seen the other tanks being
destroyed. To stay as long as they did
and to get as far as they did, I think
actually it's quite the reverse. I think
it's a tale of courage.
>> Yeah.
This excavation shows that the tragic
failure at Bullecourt was a failure of
machines and not men.
We now know that the crew of tank 796
fought bravely until their very last
shell.
We go back to the UK now where
archaeologists are investigating a huge
37-km long stretch of farmland before
the laying of a power line near
Woodbridge. Every time a major UK
building project is green-lit, then maps
have to be consulted, the land is
surveyed, and often an excavation is
carried out. Now, the archaeologists
don't set out to make spectacular finds,
but sometimes they will uncover a major
new discovery, and that's exactly what
happened this year in Suffolk.
The Suffolk landscape has been plowed
and leveled for centuries. So, when the
commercial archaeologists started work,
expectations were low.
But right at the end of the project, the
survey showed something interesting
hidden under the soil.
When they started to dig, they got a
huge surprise. It looks like this very
flat patch of land was once a hill, and
under the flattened hill, they uncover a
monumental curving ditch.
>> The scale of the the ditch is massive.
It's about 15 m wide. It's at least 2 to
3 m deep. That is a very, very large
feature, which would have been huge in
the landscape when it was around.
>> Digging this ditch must have been a
colossal undertaking, suggesting that
this was a very important site.
Through the bitterly cold winter, the
team works as fast and as carefully as
they can, peeling back each layer of
earth filling the ditch.
Then comes the next shock. There's a
perfectly preserved wooden trackway
inside the ditch that would have led to
the top of the hill.
>> The trackway itself came down on a ramp
just beside us on split oak timbers, and
then runs up along the center of the
ring ditch and terminates at the very
highest point on the hill.
>> With no precedent for such a strange
design, the team don't know if they're
looking at something that is hundreds or
thousands of years old.
But it's clear that they've unearthed an
enormous monument, and something that
had been entirely forgotten about.
As the trackway emerges, the
archaeologists can see that it's about 3
m wide, and further analysis reveals
it's made of birch and oak.
The big question is now when this
mysterious monument was constructed and
why.
And they start to find objects that
appear to have been deliberately placed
in the ditch.
>> There's an
an obvious placing of certain bones in
certain locations along the trackway,
but we're finding none of the other
bones. We're only finding pelvic bones
and jaw bones, which is sort of the
front of the animal and the back of the
animal, but nothing in between. And that
in itself is extraordinarily unusual.
>> The wood and the bone can be dated, and
they turn out to be very old indeed.
They're from 2400
BCE, so this feature is Stone Age.
At this time, we know that people were
gathering to create giant monuments in
significant places in the landscape. The
most famous of these, of course, is
Stonehenge,
which also has a large curving ditch
around it.
But there the similarities end.
This new discovery, though, raises the
possibility that many more giant
monuments could be hidden in our
landscape, each one unique and each with
its own purpose.
This henge-like monument has one last
important secret.
The team finds a large platform at the
top of the hill, built to hold the
weight of many people.
>> So, we're standing on the highest point
on the hillside where the ring ditch
occurs, and you can see behind us the
remains of the supporting structure for
the depositional platform.
>> And not only that, there are natural
springs on site that seem to have been
redirected to fill the ditch with water.
The wooden trackway and platform would
have allowed people to walk over the
water, and it seems that they were
deliberately dropping objects like the
animal bone into it.
This is an extraordinary, unique, and
puzzling feat of ancient engineering.
>> We We think that
it's part of the actual ceremonial
purpose of the platform is that people
come to the top of it and they they
deposit material to run down along the
hillside in the flowing
>> to think of a functional reason for
building a structure like this, and the
archaeologists believe it had a ritual
purpose.
>> That makes it an almost magical
experience. And if you're coming in from
the creek below, the water will be
rushing down on either side like a a
large prehistoric water feature.
>> For site director Vinny, this is the
find of a lifetime.
>> It has been a phenomenal site, a
once-in-a-career site for me. And I
think for everybody here, they've
witnessed nothing of the likes of what
we've excavated over the last 7 months.
It's been a real roller coaster.
>> I've asked the team into the lab to
explain how this remarkable site is
changing our knowledge of the ritual
landscape of prehistoric Britain.
>> That is an incredible site. And is it Is
it a henge? Can we describe it as that?
>> I think it's certainly related to those
sorts of things. Henges, we now know,
relate to water
and the use of water and presumably the
veneration of the ancestors and the
journey to the afterlife. It's quite
possible that people had their feet in
the water when they were walking along
the trackway. It's It's not a place
where they were living and and and it's
not an occupation site. Uh it's a site
with a special function.
>> So, yeah, this is the elephant in the
room. This
We've been We've been kind of ignoring
this, but it's absolutely magnificent.
So, this is a a prehistoric cow.
>> A very large prehistoric cow.
>> Yeah. I mean, it's absolutely
>> one that we we were very pleased to see
because it allowed us to have a an
indication of what they we were dealing
with because when you find an aurochs,
it tells you that whatever you've got,
it's middle Bronze Age or earlier
because they are extinct in Britain over
as of the middle Bronze Age.
>> And where did you find it?
>> So, we found this just off the end of
the platform. It's within arm's reach,
so it's deposited off the side. And
along with that, we found this
wooden-bladed agricultural artifact as
well.
>> So, it's not just a piece of wood.
>> No, it's it's a wooden spatula. It's
used for butter and milk churning. It's
the same thing you're getting the
association of agricultural practices
with the aurochs skull
in the placement at the edge of this
platform.
>> I mean, these are the earliest farmers,
aren't they? This is early Neolithic.
This is the beginning of farming in
Britain.
>> From the carbon-14 dating that we've
just had recently had back, we're
looking at it to be about 3,500 BC.
>> So, this is that's really early
Neolithic.
>> Very early. And that's from the lowest
phase of the trackway, so the very first
phase of trackway.
>> And when we're thinking of this time
period, we're we're always kind of drawn
to Stonehenge just because that is such
an obvious feature still in our
landscape. It's quite curious to see
that there were things like this that
have been forgotten about.
>> Stonehenge is famous for its kind of
lifespan.
Now, what we can tell from this site in
particular is that it has a similar
lifespan. Outside of our site from the
surveying that we've done also, we can
see there's a much larger sequence of
monumental activity in that whole valley
side, which is prehistoric. It's
something that those people and their
descendants have
kept coming back to for thousands of
years.
>> This astonishing site reveals that our
prehistoric ancestors came together to
build a spectacular water feature and
returned here over more than a thousand
years.
But unlike Stonehenge, this monument was
flattened and lost until now.
It's still early days, but the
Woodbridge site looks set to become the
stuff of archaeological legend.
We cover many exciting digs on this
series, but in fact, the excavation is
only the start of a long journey of
discovery. Once finds and samples are
retrieved, they're sent off to labs for
conservation and analysis, a process
that can take weeks, months, sometimes
even years. And for this next dig in
Chichester, it is only when the samples
arrive in the lab that the real details
begin to emerge.
Field archaeologist Raksha Dave is
traveling to Portslade to find out how
post-excavation work following a
Chichester dig is making sense of
Britain's lost landscapes.
>> For the last 2 years, Southern Water
have been laying a 10 km pipeline
cutting through town and country and
they paid Archaeology Southeast to
monitor their work.
As they dug the areas where the pipes
[music] were to be laid, they found
prehistoric henges, Roman settlement and
burial, and RAF bases from World War II.
But most intriguingly,
they have unearthed a buried medieval
village.
There are an awful lot of buckets here.
>> Yeah, absolutely. Yes. So, these are
just some of the hundreds of samples
that we've recovered from the village
itself. They are soil basically from
archaeological deposits like for example
fills of ditches and pits.
>> So you've got a plan here. As they
excavated along the line of the future
water pipe and uncovered the footprint
of the lost village. They mapped the
details.
>> So you can see there's boundary ditches,
there's post holes relating to
structures.
>> To access this time capsule of medieval
life. They've dug up entire sections of
the ground and brought them back to the
lab.
The clues to the people who lived in
this village are hidden in the soil.
But first they need to get rid of a lot
of mud.
>> Good grief. Then do I just break these
bits up then?
>> Yeah.
>> So
>> All we're trying to do is break it down.
So the water will do some of the work
for us.
>> This is a quite a bizarre job.
>> It is.
>> It's like what do you do for a living?
Oh, I'm washing mud.
>> It's almost like a massage in it.
Very intimate.
What we're trying to do is get rid of
all the soil so we end up with all the
lovely archaeological material.
>> I can actually feel all the tiny bits.
>> Yeah. This one on top of this mesh will
have all the heavy stuff.
>> With the
>> weights float but then some lighter
things like charcoal and plant remains
will float and we'll end up with them in
this smaller one.
>> The large tank at the top will catch
stone, tile, and metal. And the small
mesh below it catches lighter plant
remains.
>> So how do you then use all of this
information about this organic remains
to paint a picture of village life?
>> Yeah, for example we have a sample with
lots of charcoal in it. It could be from
an oven or a kiln. We can identify
certain types of charcoal as being fuel
wood.
>> Yeah, so you can see where they're
selecting certain types of trees to burn
and if they're avoiding any, whether
they're cutting down trees to use as
fuel or whether they are just picking
from the forest floor. It just amazes me
how much information you can get from
such a tiny piece of charcoal.
>> Extracting all of this information
requires an expert [music] eye. So, they
are passed to archaeobotanist Angela for
analysis.
>> Gosh, this is quite painstaking stuff.
>> And then I go
I listen to music when I do
>> [laughter]
>> These innocuous bits of seed and
charcoal can give us an intimate insight
into the everyday lives of the people in
this village.
Germinated grains showed that they were
brewing ale.
The charcoal shows us where they were
cooking. And the cereal can tell us
about the bread they were eating.
>> In medieval times, both wheat and barley
were used for making flour because wheat
was a bit of a high-status cereal. So,
uh not everybody could afford to eat
bread that was made entirely out of
wheat.
>> After all of these samples are sorted
and analyzed, the team will be able to
work out what people were doing in
different parts of the site.
And the larger finds from the excavation
are providing intriguing clues to the
village's fate.
>> Where has this [music] material come
from?
>> Well, all of this tile has come from a
spread that was overlying um one side of
the best-preserved house that we had in
the site.
>> We know that there are two thousand
fragments of tile here weighing close to
40 kg, and that's a significantly large
amount to get from a single feature.
>> Tile was a valuable resource and often
reused. Such a large quantity left
untouched after the building's collapse
suggests that the entire village was
abandoned.
>> So, it's literally collapsed down, and
all the tiles just spread onto the
ground.
>> it drops, yeah.
>> The fabric of this particular tile is
quite distinctive. You can see it's got
quite large flint inclusions. And we can
say that it's between 1150 and 1350 AD.
>> This medieval date gives an important
clue as to why this village disappeared.
>> Well, that's a classic feature of the
deserted medieval village in the
mid-14th century where
you just get obviously massive
depopulation. You're going into a cold
phase that hits around the time of the
so-called Little Ice Age.
That has a knock-on effect with like
the impact on food and harvest. You've
got the Black Death rolls in around that
time. You've got the Hundred Years' War
as well, which would have been a drain
on the population.
When you combine them all together, it
must have been pretty pretty
devastating.
>> The date of this collapsed building
shows that the perfect storm of climate
change, disease, and political turmoil
signaled the end for this particular
village.
It's early days, but it's likely these
buckets of mud hold many more of the
village's secrets for the archaeologists
to uncover.
>> Our next site takes us to the village of
Great Wenham in Suffolk where a team
were brought in to investigate a small
field ahead of a housing project because
evidence of Roman activity had already
been found in the surrounding area.
>> This dig is making us question Roman
burial practice in Britain.
>> When it comes to the Romans, a fort or a
villa looks very similar whether it's in
northern Africa or eastern Britain.
So, archaeologists often half know what
they're going to find even before they
start digging. But, some sites defy all
the expectations.
>> When the team arrived on site, they
found evidence of burials.
There's nothing unusual about this, but
it meant the site had to be fully
excavated.
5 weeks in, they make what seems to be a
gruesome discovery.
>> So, I've got a child between about 4 and
8 years old.
And he's what we call a deviant burial,
which means it's been uh placed in an
unusual way or buried in an unusual
practice. You can see
the head has been removed from where it
should be and is in between the legs.
So, we've got the arms coming down like
this. The two legs on either side, which
are spread, and the head right in the
middle.
>> There are examples of strange burials
like this, decapitated with the head
rearranged, from other Roman cemeteries.
But, they're rare, and we don't know why
the dead body would be treated in this
way.
As the dig continues, there are plenty
of more normal-looking graves. So, it
looks like the deviant burial is a
one-off.
But, it isn't.
>> Uh so far, I'm uncovering this grave
where we have this skeleton, possibly
deviant. We're not entirely sure yet if
the skull belongs to this skeleton, but
I believe it could be from this skeleton
because by the pelvis and by the skull,
it seems to be female.
>> This burial is even stranger than the
last.
>> So, we also have feet, but they do not
belong to this skeleton. So, it's
obvious that we have several redeposits
on the same grave.
>> This body appears to have been buried
with an extra pair of feet, which must
have been removed from their owner fully
fleshed.
Over the next few days, more deviant
burials emerge.
>> We're missing the top vertebrae from
over here, so it's very likely that this
skull
does belong to this individual, and
we've got clear evidence of decapitation
having occurred on site. So, we've got
yet another deviant burial.
>> We have another presumed decapitation
where the head has been placed
underneath the lower limbs.
>> And we have Bruner excavating our 17th
decapitation burial.
This is actually the 17th out of 32,
which show deviancy in the form of
decapitation with the head out of its
correct anatomical position.
>> Well over half of the people buried in
this cemetery have been decapitated.
And even more peculiarly, several have
extra body parts with them.
This is a large number of deviant
burials for a single cemetery.
So, what does it mean?
I've asked Rebecca Redfern from the
Museum of London and lead archaeologist
Carrie Ball into the lab to help solve
this mystery.
>> I I suppose what's absolutely crucial to
understand about this, you know, we talk
about decapitation, but what we what we
need to try to understand is whether
that is somebody being beheaded as the
cause of their death, or whether
actually they're already dead and you're
removing the head of a dead body.
>> I I think in this case, with this with
this particular woman, I think we're
facing more of a funerary ritual rather
than as an execution. I mean, the
cemetery is very is very strange, so
>> mean, what we do seem to have all of the
decapitation burials, they have
purposely moved the head from anatomical
position, and they tend to have it in
the lower limb area. So, it seemed to
have been important to them to remove
that head and put them somewhere else.
Whereas, normally with some sort of
execution burials, all you need to do is
chop off the head and kill them.
>> I mean, I think this is obviously part
of a culture where this is happening
after death. This is just what you do
with the dead body and it's kind of
assumed in the same way that you know,
what we do with dead bodies now is
cremate them, grind them up and put them
in a pot. And and there's not
necessarily thought going into that
process every time.
>> But where do you think it comes from?
What's the motivation?
>> It's really interesting cuz a lot of the
time a lot of the decapitation or even
prone burials so people are buried face
down or in unusual positions, they're
covered with stones. And so we think
that is like definitely we are
making sure you never come back.
>> So can you tell anything about this
other individual here?
>> I mean, this lady appears to have
experienced quite a physical lifestyle.
If we look at her elbow joint, it's very
shiny.
>> It's lovely shiny, yeah.
>> It looks like ivory, doesn't it? So
she's lost all the cartilage there.
>> Yeah, in her elbow and then again in her
wrist at the bottom of the ulna.
>> Yeah.
>> And then her finger phalanges, one
appears to be broken and one appears to
be infected. And there it seems to be a
little bit of joint disease as well in
her skeleton and all of the maxillary
teeth have been lost and lost for quite
a long time cuz it's all pinched back
together.
>> Yeah.
>> And it's made her face look very kind of
caved in.
>> Yeah.
>> It's not something that I would really
expect to see because she doesn't appear
to be that old.
>> Do we have any idea
who these people might have been, you
know, where they stood in Roman society?
>> There's a site down the road where
they've actually found a slave manacle
of around about the same period and so
maybe we could have a funeral right
associated with slave burials and that's
why we're getting a lot of this
degenerative bone disease reflecting
that kind of lifestyle.
>> Do you think that's a reasonable
hypothesis?
>> I think so. For the Romans to really
kind of get the rural economy going,
they have to import a huge number of
people both from the continent but also
they're moving people around Britain and
they're enslaved.
>> And that's really interesting too cuz
when we when we look at Roman Britain,
we're often talking about the civilized
nature of it. But here we've got
something that prefigures medieval
serfdom.
>> Oh, absolutely. We know one of the big
exports in the late Iron Age are slaves
from Britain. So, the Romans just really
ramp that um part of the economy up. And
also the fact that anyone could be a
slave. You get people who may not show
us that they've suffered a hard
childhood because they might have had a
fairly affluent life, but then become
enslaved as adults.
And that's what we're seeing. So, it's a
very, very complicated, but for me, for
the research that I've done, I would say
this is very convincing.
>> This This is a slave cemetery.
>> Yes.
>> We still don't really understand why
these bodies were decapitated.
But by identifying these people as
slaves, the cemetery could help to shed
light on that darker side of Roman rule.
Now, we travel forward in time 1,200
years to Hampshire and a chance
discovery of a stash of coins that might
throw some light on one of the most
turbulent periods in our British
history.
In April 2018, Canadian metal
detectorist Darcy Fear was holidaying in
Hampshire.
Back home, he'd been passionate about
his hobby for decades, even though he'd
had little success.
>> Thursday morning, it was a beautiful
day.
I started metal detecting and it was my
first signal. I was only there 10, 15
minutes.
And I was just so amazed that I found
something so incredible.
>> Darcy's holiday was about to become the
archaeological experience of a lifetime.
>> When I dug the top of the soil and then
I saw the first bit of pottery on the
ground, and then
the last shovel full when we lifted it
out, it was just coins everywhere. So,
it was we knew what what we had dinner.
I did anyway, so yeah.
>> Incredibly having just arrived in the
UK, Darcy had discovered a hoard of
buried coins.
All the visible ones were nearly 400
years old. They'd probably been hidden
here in the Civil War.
During the English Civil War, the
country was split, torn apart by
fighting between Charles I's
Royalists and Cromwell's Roundheads.
But while the history books can provide
us with details of the battles and the
blood sheds, the names of leaders even,
archaeology reveals the details of
ordinary lives.
Although on foreign turf, Darcy knew
exactly what he should do when he made
his discovery.
>> I know the rules, so we're not supposed
to touch anything once you find a hoard,
and so we didn't until we got a hold of
an archaeologist.
By the end of the day, they finally let
us dig it ourselves.
>> Having sought permission and then with
careful supervision, the hoard was
lifted.
>> Then we put the whole thing into a
bucket to keep it together and then
cover it with a wet rag. And then, you
know, the bucket alone weighed 100 lb.
This was mostly dirt.
>> By taking such care, Darcy and the
archaeologist hoped that they'd removed
the entire hoard in a single block.
And then, the conservation team at the
British Museum take over.
>> Very quickly after I started excavating,
I started seeing the rim of the vessel,
which was very lucky because then I
realized this is what I was working
with.
>> The pot looks to be intact, meaning that
it could be just as its owner had placed
it there 400 years ago.
So, Duygu begins to work very slowly and
methodically.
>> This is really a micro-excavation, so if
if I was on site,
um excavating your find, this is exactly
what would for when I'm doing it, yeah.
>> Diyigu carries out this mini dig with
almost surgical skill.
And she notices something remarkable
about the way the coins were placed
inside the pot.
>> It looks like in this layer that I've
been excavating, the coins are stuck
next to each other and upwards.
>> It's hard to believe really, you know,
to find something like this.
>> Senior Conservator Pippa Pearce thinks
that the owner of the hoard had sorted
the money into neat little stacks.
Someone who clearly intended to come
back to them.
>> Cuz that would mean that they were in a
hurry, they weren't about to be
murdered. They weren't counting their
money out neatly and then just putting
it into a pot and hiding it.
>> And the stacks of silver coins just keep
on coming.
>> So, we've got 23 coins out at the
moment. You reckon there's as many again
or more?
>> I think there's 200 coins in there.
>> Woah.
>> The coins are in great condition despite
being in the ground for so long.
>> So, you can see his beard.
>> These ones are in nice shape.
>> Yes, very little corrosion.
>> You see the dates on those ones as plain
as day. Amazing.
>> So, to have what is a really [laughter]
good condition hoard and to be able to
excavate it in the lab is just brilliant
for us.
>> So, why did this person bury their
wealth?
I'm speaking to British [music] Museum
coin expert Barry Cook to find out more
about this incredible hoard.
>> So, we've got Edward the VI all the way
through Elizabeth, James through to
Charles.
What's the time depth there?
>> We have 100 years pretty much of English
monarchy.
>> Yeah.
>> We could have had older coins except
that Henry VIII debased the coinage and
left it in a terrible state. So, it was
up to his children, Edward the VI, Mary,
and Elizabeth to try and sort that out.
Uh Edward and Mary both issued good
silver coins, but they didn't get rid of
the the terrible stuff. Elizabeth came
in and got rid of all the bad money.
>> Yeah.
>> So, civil war hoards, the oldest coin
will often be an Edward the VI or a a
Mary coin.
>> Yeah. I mean, it seems quite
extraordinary to us today, I think, to
imagine that people were still using
coins that were 100 years old and they
were still
>> Yes, got two young people too young.
I can remember Edward the VII coins.
>> Yeah.
>> You have the pre-decimalization.
>> The coins didn't change.
And you you don't you don't withdraw the
coins cuz they're really old. You keep
them there.
>> So, who else have we got?
>> James the I.
There are some coins left dates on, but
most coins of this period do not have
dates on.
>> Oh.
>> But the mint organizes production by
putting a little mark on so you can date
those.
>> And then finally,
>> Charles. This is a nice shilling of
Charles. We used to have these shillings
as 12 for 12 pence.
>> Yeah. So, he's the last one.
>> He's the latest one in the hoard and the
hoard ends with a lot of coins of his
from one particular mint mark, which is
called triangle and circle because
obviously it's a triangle inside a
circle. And that was the mark that was
being used between 1641 and 1643.
>> Right.
>> And that's really important cuz in 1642,
the king leaves London, the civil war
starts.
>> Yeah.
>> So, this is the coinage being produced
as the civil war is just beginning.
>> Yeah.
>> And you get a lot of coin hoards that
end at this time. So, everyone is hiding
their money.
>> And is there anything else unusual about
this? I mean, the the the scratching out
of faces seems to be quite odd. Is that
something we often see?
>> Yes, uh to a degree. It's not not every
hoard has got these scratches, but um
enough of them do for it to be a a
serious phenomenon of the period.
>> Yeah.
>> Uh we don't really understand why they
did it. And this hoard is typical in the
sense that
most of the scratch coins are shillings.
And most of the scratch coins are
Elizabeth. So, if you would imagine if
there was a political motive during the
civil war of scratching the king's face
out, it's going to be Charles. It's not
Elizabeth. Elizabeth was viewed as in a
in a more positive light. She was the
comparison that against against which
the Stuarts failed.
>> Yeah. So, what is the explanation for
these scratches, then?
>> I'm inclined to think there is some sort
of practical explanation. You might just
be keeping track. You might be
accounting. It might be the top one in
the pile. It could be something like
that. Who knows?
>> So, with a coin hoard like this,
sometimes with earlier coin hoards we're
left we're left wondering whether
perhaps they're votive offerings or
people burying their their wealth.
>> This is this is pure
hiding your economic wealth and hoping
to come back to it.
>> Yeah.
>> We're at the point where the England is
collapsing, disintegrating, and people
are hiding their coins,
hiding everything they can get and put
it in the in the ground. And generally
speaking, the hoards are found in across
the country where the two sides are
meeting.
>> Right.
>> They sort of sweep down in the bottom of
Yorkshire and then through through the
the Midlands and then where where the
king's headquarters was into the West
Country where the two armies are always
meeting. They do reflect how the war was
working.
>> They reflect that clash.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. [snorts]
And in terms of the wealth that was
buried here, can you give me an
equivalent?
>> It's £13, 4 shillings, and 6 pence.
>> Yeah, which doesn't sound like an a lot
today, but how much was it then?
>> Well, that's very easily an annual
salary of a worker.
>> Yeah.
>> They used to say that the citizens and
gentlemen should be able to live off £10
a year.
>> Right.
>> We're a bit later now, but you know, £13
is is a good income for pretty much
anyone who wasn't a gentleman or a
really rich trader.
>> Yeah. So, in that pot we've got a small
fortune.
>> Yes, so we have somebody's annual wages.
>> Yeah. And they never came back to
retrieve it.
>> Something happened.
>> Mhm.
>> Next, we travel to Coldingham, right at
the English-Scottish border, in pursuit
of a powerful but forgotten Anglo-Saxon
princess.
This site lies just across the water
from the famous Lindisfarne Abbey.
Lindisfarne was founded by King Oswald,
who is still famous today for
transforming Britain into a Christian
country.
But the role his sister played has often
been overlooked.
Rejecting the traditional option of
marriage, Princess Eabba became an
abbess and played a crucial part in the
spread of this religion.
But the precise location of her
monastery has proved elusive.
A team of archaeologists and volunteers
from Dig Ventures is hoping to put Ebba
back into the story of how Christianity
spread.
>> So, I hold something on this side.
>> Yeah.
>> So, we're here at Coldingham looking for
Saint Ebba's monastery, an Anglo-Saxon
double monastery that we think was
somewhere around the location.
The abbey that Ebba established would
have acted as a vital link between the
evangelical monks of Lindisfarne and the
people on the mainland they needed to
reach.
The hunt starts near a later Norman
priory, often placed on the site of an
older abbey.
But the remains of these Saxon abbeys
are incredibly elusive. There are often
no stone buildings to find. So, even
discovering the site of a chapel can be
difficult. But there usually is a marked
boundary.
>> We started to clean back along this
trench, and what's really exciting is we
started to find some archaeological
features. What we think we found is a
ditch which is similar to the 7th
century ditch found at earlier
excavations.
>> A ditch dating to the 7th century was
found in a nearby field 13 years ago.
And if this new ditch connects to that
one, it could suggest that they're on
the very edge of the monastery site.
The team have just 12 more days to find
solid evidence.
But with a good start like this, they're
feeling confident.
>> Maybe a tiny bit of tile or something.
>> But then some surprising material begins
to emerge.
>> Bones
coming out of everywhere.
This whole layer this full of it.
>> These are animal bones.
>> We are halfway through week two and we
have loads and loads of animal bone
which makes me desperate and happy at
the same time. Happy because it's really
exciting but desperate because we only
have four days to clean it all.
>> While heaps of animal bones might not be
the evidence the team is expecting, it
is interesting.
The quantity of animal bones suggests
that something more than just the
consumption of meat was happening here.
>> We might have a tannery here making
leather,
glue,
tallow for candles. There's all sorts of
things they'd have been using um animals
for.
>> The bones and the boundary ditch won't
reveal their secrets until long after
this short dig is over and dating work
can be done.
But it's a promising start to an
archaeological quest to give Eadburh the
recognition she deserves.
Even when women held positions of power
and were written about in historical
texts, they seem to have been
selectively forgotten about.
300 miles south in Essex, another team
is uncovering the story of another
powerful Anglo-Saxon woman.
A new shopping center is planned for the
center of Barking giving the team from
Thames Valley Archaeological Services a
chance to dig. And they're on the trail
of another elusive monastery.
In Anglo-Saxon Britain, the growth and
success of a town was often linked to
the presence of an economically powerful
abbey.
And in Barking, that success built on
the work of a princess called Æthelburh
who we know founded the first monastery
there.
Our next dig is providing tantalizing
evidence of Saxon occupation, industry,
and trade, which is probably linked to
her Abbey.
>> They start digging where some
Anglo-Saxon buildings were found back in
the '80s, and soon they find something
promising.
>> So, this is day
12 of our excavation at Barking Abbey.
We're looking at Saxon building. Just
this morning, I'm discovering that it's
starting to look like it's sunken floor
building, like a grub hut perhaps, but
maybe a grub hut that's used in the
church.
>> A grub hut is a characteristic
Anglo-Saxon building with a sunken
floor.
So, they decide to dig down through this
pit, hoping they're on the right track.
>> I found that.
>> Very nice.
>> Looks like a rusty old bit of barbed
wire in there, but I'm pretty convinced
that that's a copper alloy pin. And it
almost looks like that's like a bone or
something like that.
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> So, maybe it's something that goes like
in a nun's hair or a hole for a pin.
>> Twist.
>> That's a hairpin.
>> To to a hairpin.
>> [laughter]
>> This hairpin might be tiny, but it's a
potentially prestigious item that could
have been worn by a wealthy Anglo-Saxon
woman.
Then later that day, Graham's expert eye
spots something else.
>> Oh, wow.
We've found a little piece of Saxon
period glass coming out of the building
that we're calling the chapel. And
that's probably from the 8th century.
>> Wow.
>> Which is
exciting.
>> Yeah.
>> Archaeologists get excited about tiny
little bits of glass, but
>> There's every reason to be excited. In
Anglo-Saxon Britain, glass was a rare
luxury, and perhaps not so unexpected
here if there was a monastery on this
site.
The team settle in to comb every inch of
this sunken feature, because the tiniest
piece of evidence could make all the
difference.
But that afternoon, they find something
that tells them far more than they'd
ever expected.
>> We found a piece of millefiori rod
that was on top of a burnt layer.
>> Oh, that is gorgeous.
>> There it is.
>> These rods are essentially offcuts from
making fine glassware.
So this could be powerful evidence that
there is a rare Anglo-Saxon glass
factory on this site.
>> We've got evidence of consumption of
glassware in the form of glass vessels,
but we're now starting to get evidence
of production of glasswork in Saxon
period. There's probably less than five
Saxon period glass production sites in
Britain. So to find that really is very
exciting.
>> These finds give us tantalizing glimpses
of Anglo-Saxon life.
But do they confirm the presence of an
Abbey?
The new site director, Kyle, explains
more in the lab.
We saw some film of uncovering a grub
house of kind of sunken floored
building. Do you think it was it a
chapel?
>> Unfortunately, when we got to the bottom
of this supposed sunken feature
building, we found some plastic lining.
So it turned out that this was back
filled.
>> How frustrating.
>> It was very frustrating.
>> Cuz you were all that digging thinking
you were digging into pristine
stratified layers and then and then you
get down and find out that it's been
disturbed.
>> Yes, so we found quite a few nice finds
in in it as well, which suggested that
at least these soils were part of the
monastery.
>> So what have we got here?
>> So here we've got the bird head pin.
>> Oh yeah. Yeah.
>> So this is quite a high status object
and this here we think is the top of an
incense burner.
So that kind of ties into the idea that
there there was sort of religious
ceremony going on.
>> But I think that for me one of the one
of the things that really caught my eye
and seems quite important
is that which is just a bit of leftover
glass from making glass, but it's the
fact that they were making glass that's
that's so interesting.
>> Yeah, I know there's there's definitely
evidence there to point towards them
making glass in the area and we know
that there was supposedly a glass
working facility around the Abbey, but
unfortunately we didn't actually find
the structure that we're hoping to.
>> You know, tantalizing glimpses,
artifacts that definitely date to the
right time period, but as yet Barking
Abbey remains
a bit elusive. Yeah. Yeah.
So they have the right finds at Barking,
but no monastery. At Coldingham it's the
opposite, few finds, but possibly a
monastery boundary. I've asked Mandy
Foster into the lab to explain her
findings.
>> So is this your plan from from this
year?
Can you can you talk me through it? It
is quite complicated.
>> What we're focusing on here
really in terms of our Anglo-Saxon
monastery and looking for Ebba is this
feature here that comes through. And you
think that's the ditch? Yeah, I thought
it's the ditch and hopefully we'll prove
it later, but if you imagine zooming out
where I'm standing, I'm pretty much in
the priory grounds.
>> And this is this is the perimeter.
>> And this is the perimeter. It's if we
could establish that what we do have
here is the vallum ditch.
And we can start to pull together some
more of the evidence that we've seen. If
we've got the dates in the right places
and we've got small artifacts, these
really start to point towards this as
being the monastic community for Ebba's
site.
>> And actually it's the it's the ditch
that's that's more interesting.
>> small ditch that was really quietly
empty.
>> [laughter]
>> But with environmental deposits and
that's the thing. I mean what you don't
always get in an archaeological site is
tons of material culture, loads of finds
that really point to things and lots of
shiny stuff. I mean sometimes you do
just find soil
and cuts and features.
>> Yeah. And how important do you think
this monastery and Ever herself was to
the the spread of Christianity? In this
area.
>> Yeah. She was brought up in a family
with seven brothers, three of which were
then kings. They set up between the
monasteries all over Northumbria. These
were real power centers, you know, she
was a powerful woman with a large part
of an economy around her.
>> Fascinating how involved women were in
powerful positions in the in the early
Anglo-Saxon church, I think.
>> It's kind of moments in history where
some women were able to really have that
kind of
equal power with men as well.
>> Yeah. And I think that's something that
disappears later.
>> Yeah. Certainly by the establishment of
the Norman religious communities, women
can no longer go into the shrine of St.
Cuthbert, which is around the Norman
time. So, within a really short space of
time, you've got women that are powerful
enough to be able to set up monastic
communities as a lead and to have this
kind of really strong economic position
in a society and then within
a couple of hundred years, they can't go
into a shrine anymore.
>> In Anglo-Saxon England, women pretty
much had two choices, [music]
marriage or the church, something that
could create a bit of an identity
crisis.
>> One of the tiniest objects in the
Norwich Castle Museum reveals this
story.
>> This is a metal detector find that was
made in 1998. It's I think one of the
most remarkable things that we've had
brought in through metal detecting in
the last 20 years.
>> What is it?
>> It's a seal matrix. In other words, the
thing that was used to make the
impression that makes a seal.
>> Yeah.
>> And this was actually within a ring, a
gold finger ring, and it would have spun
on the gold rod that runs through the
center of it.
>> I can just about spot that gold rod
there. And it's got a It's got a name on
it.
>> It says Balthildis, or Balthild, which
is a female name.
>> And do we have any idea who this woman
is?
>> We've got one historical figure called
Balthild, an Anglo-Saxon sold into
slavery and bought by the mayor of the
court in 7th century France.
And she then becomes queen, and
ultimately she takes on the role of
regent.
And she rules the kingdom in her own
right.
>> So, this historical Balthild,
I mean, she's a really good candidate
for the person that would have had an
object like this. This is This is high
status. It implies that somebody is
literate.
>> Absolutely. It ticks all of the right
boxes.
>> So, why is it on a rod?
>> It's on a rod so that it actually
rotates on that. So, you have the public
side with her name on it, but if you
rotate it,
you can see a couple in an intimate
embrace beneath a cross.
>> Okay, I wasn't expecting that.
But I know it's actually quite rude. I
mean, I can see genitals.
>> Yeah, it is. I mean, it it could be an
arm coming out very low down on the
body, but I don't think it is.
>> [laughter]
>> I'm an anatomist, and I don't I don't
think I know what I'm looking at here.
>> It is a remarkable thing.
>> But combined with a with a cross,
this seems to be a very peculiar image.
>> It might suggest something like a
betrothal ring. And in this particular
case, if she goes into a nunnery, maybe
she's there for a bride of Christ, and
that's why she's beneath a cross.
>> It's quite curious cuz I think in a
single object it almost encapsulates the
choices that were there for high status
Anglo-Saxon women. You're either a wife
and a mother, or you're a nun.
And it combines those double identities.
>> It does, and it also speaks of the power
of these early women as well. I mean,
Balthild is somebody that founds a
monastery at Chelles, and when she loses
political power, sure enough, she's
obliged to go into Chelles as a nun
herself in about 665. And there she
remains until she dies in about 680. And
then, 11 years later, she's pronounced a
saint.
>> Archaeology can reveal entirely new
information about our ancestors, as well
as giving us a tangible link to people
whose stories have been largely
forgotten.
Getting closer to the physical of the
monasteries these women founded will
hopefully put them back in the picture.
This program has shown how every new
excavation forces us to re-evaluate the
story of Britain. From discovering how
Stone Age people were more prolific
monument builders than we ever realized
>> That makes it an almost magical
experience. The water will be rushing
down on either side like a a large
prehistoric water feature.
>> To the treatment of slaves after death
under Roman rule.
And the outstanding bravery of the men
facing the worst horrors of the First
World War.
Through archaeology, we are able [music]
to reach back and touch their lives.
>> [snorts]